<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to M. Cawdry's two books of the Sabbath, lately come forth Wherein the author doth two things: 1. He vindicates himselfe from Mr Cawdrie's unfriendly abuse of him, in fathering upon him three texts of scripture, and three arguments deduced from them, to prove the perpetuity of the antient Sabbath, ... Wherein the author hath 1. Answered and confuted all that Mr. Cawdry hath wrote to corrupt the sense and meaning of the Commandement. 2. He hath restored the antient, genuine, and proper sense of the Commandement: and confirmed it by sundry undeniable arguments. By Theophilus Brabourne.</title>
            <author>Brabourne, Theophilus, b. 1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77209</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4088</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229562</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895458</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895458</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152852</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77209)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152852)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2327:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to M. Cawdry's two books of the Sabbath, lately come forth Wherein the author doth two things: 1. He vindicates himselfe from Mr Cawdrie's unfriendly abuse of him, in fathering upon him three texts of scripture, and three arguments deduced from them, to prove the perpetuity of the antient Sabbath, ... Wherein the author hath 1. Answered and confuted all that Mr. Cawdry hath wrote to corrupt the sense and meaning of the Commandement. 2. He hath restored the antient, genuine, and proper sense of the Commandement: and confirmed it by sundry undeniable arguments. By Theophilus Brabourne.</title>
                  <author>Brabourne, Theophilus, b. 1590.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 102 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for William Franklin, and are to be sold at Norwich,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Identified as Wing B4088, reel 2327, of the UMI microfilm set, "Early English books, 1641-1700".</note>
                  <note>Cf. Wing B4088 which has "W. Franklin" in the imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Dr. Williams' Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ten Commandments --  Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sunday --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152852:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Anſwer To M. <hi>Cawdry's</hi> two Books of the Sabbath, Lately come forth.</p>
            <p>Wherein the Author doth two things: 1. He vindicates himſelfe from Mr <hi>Cawdrie's</hi> unfriendly abuſe of him, in fathering upon him three Texts of Scripture, and three Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments deduced from them, to prove the perpetuity of the antient Sabbath, which the Author doth in no caſe own. 2. He vindicates the fourth Commandement from M. <hi>Cawdry's</hi> falſe Expoſition of it.</p>
            <p>Wherein the Author hath 1. Anſwered and confuted all that Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> hath wrote to corrupt the ſenſe and meaning of the Commandement. 2. He hath reſtored the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, genuine, and proper ſenſe of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: and confirmed it by ſundry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Arguments.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Theophilus Brabourne.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 5 18, 19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill heaven and earth paſſe away, one jot, or one tittle ſhall in no wiſe paſſe from the Law. Whoſoever therefore ſhall break one of theſe leaſt Commandements, and ſhall <hi>teach</hi> men ſo, he ſhall be leaſt in the kingdome of heaven.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Franklin,</hi> and are to be ſold at <hi>Norwich.</hi> 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152852:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152852:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>Jude</hi> exhorts us, that we ſhould <hi>earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contend for the truth,</hi> which was <hi>once delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> unto the <hi>Saints.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> complaines of men in his time, who <hi>bent</hi> their <hi>tongues</hi> like <hi>Bows</hi> for lies: but they were not <hi>valiant</hi> or <hi>couragious</hi> for the <hi>Truth, Jer. 9.3.</hi> If ever St <hi>Jude's</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation was needfull in the Church, it is now needfull: when the truth, or true doctrine of the Sabbath, once delivered to the Saints, is ſo ſhamefully corrupted and abuſed. If ever
<pb facs="tcp:152852:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> there was a time when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> complaint was verified, now is the time: Do not men now, yea, <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and of all miniſters thoſe accounted the moſt forward, hot, and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, do not theſe bend their tongues like bows for lies? And doth not <hi>Mr Cawdry</hi> appeare in the <hi>front,</hi> by his three books of about twelve ſhillings price, though to little purpoſe? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe expoſitions of the fourth Commandement be truths or falſities, I leave my Reader to judge, after he hath read this little Booke. They ſay, firſt, So be it we give God <hi>a day</hi> for his Sabbath, it matters not what day, be it Saturday or Sunday: As if God had never made <hi>choi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> of his day: They might as well ſay, So be it we have a <hi>man</hi> to diſpenſe the Sacraments,
<pb facs="tcp:152852:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> it matters not what man, be he Miniſter or Lay-man. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, They ſay, God did not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in his fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>the</hi> Sabbath day, as of a certaine day definitely, but <hi>a</hi> Sabbath day, as of ſome uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine day indefinitely; as if God delivered his Commandements in <hi>ambiguous</hi> terms, and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full words; as if no man could know by the Commandement what day God meant his people ſhould keep for his Sabbath day. Thirdly, They ſay, by the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall word <hi>ſeventh</hi> in the fourth Commandement, we need not underſtand Saturday the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth and laſt day of the week; but any one day of the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ven, as Sunday the firſt day of the weeke; as if when God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the <hi>laſt</hi> day of the week we may underſtand him of the
<pb facs="tcp:152852:4"/> 
               <hi>firſt</hi> day of the weeke. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whereas God <hi>reſted</hi> at the Creation on Saturday the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day for our <hi>imitation;</hi> they ſay, we may <hi>imitate</hi> Gods example if we reſt on Sunday the firſt day; as if we imitated Gods example by <hi>croſſing</hi> of it: for he reſted at the end of the weeke, and we reſt at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the weeke. Fifthly, They ſay, the fourth Commandement enjoyned the <hi>Jews</hi> to keep Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday; &amp; the ſame fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement enjoynes <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to keepe Sunday; as if one and the ſame Commandement ſhould enjoyns contrary things: as the Saturday, which they call <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſme,</hi> and the Sunday, or Lords day, which they call their <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath:</hi> and ſo it ſhall enjoyne both <hi>Judaiſme</hi> and <hi>Chriſtia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſme:</hi> and ſo the
<pb facs="tcp:152852:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> fourth Commandement ſhall have one ſenſe and meaning yeſterday, and another this day: for thouſands of yeares till Chriſt it ſhall have one expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as for Saturday; and for ever after Chriſt it ſhall have another expoſition, as for Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. Now to make up the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>ſeven abominations</hi> Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> will adde two more as theſe enſuing. Sixthly, The Sabbath day and ſeventh day, mentioned in the fourth Commandement, are not the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, but one day in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is the ſubſtance: as if the words <hi>expreſſed</hi> in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement ſhould be no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and yet one day in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ven, which words are not expreſſed, ſhould be the ſubſtance of it. Seventhly, The Sabbath day
<pb facs="tcp:152852:5"/> and ſeventh day, mentioned in the fourth Commandement are <hi>indirectly</hi> commanded, but one day of ſeven, of which there are no ſuch words in the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and yet theſe are <hi>direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> commanded, as he ſaith. Was there ever any of God's ten Commandements thus ſhattered by <hi>Jeſuites?</hi> and thus wrung and wreſted from the genuine and true ſenſe intended by God? and yet theſe are the expoſitions given by the godly Miniſters: Now may I not juſtly take up the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of theſe ſo zealous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, ſaying, They bend their tongues like <hi>Bows</hi> to publiſh falſe Expoſitions of Gods fourth Commandement? The Lord threatned old <hi>Eli</hi> the Prieſt, ſaying, <hi>They that deſpiſe me ſhall be deſpiſed, 1</hi> Sam. <hi>2.30.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152852:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> And have not theſe Miniſters deſpiſed God by corrupting the ſenſe of one of his ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements? And hath not God of late deſpiſed them? Never did God poure greater contempt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Clergy men than in our daies, wherein they are aſhamed to weare black Coats, and turne into colours.</p>
            <p>Theſe things premiſed, now I ſhall give my Reader an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count how far I have anſwered Mr <hi>Cawdry's</hi> Books: He hath wrote three books of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath: the firſt part about ſeven yeares agone, the other two parts now lately; I do not undertake to anſwer all that he hath wrote, for many things he hath wrote, not againſt me, but in confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Biſhop of <hi>Eli,</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>White's</hi> Book, which was an Anſwer unto my <hi>ſecond</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152852:6"/> Booke of the <hi>Sabbath:</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly againſt what I wrote in it, in maintenance of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Sabbath: but <hi>granting</hi> what I wrote againſt the <hi>Lords day</hi> Sabbath: And divers things he hath wrote againſt Dr <hi>Heyline,</hi> and againſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Primroſe:</hi> Now I leave theſe things unto their proper Authors: I meddle with no more than with what he hath wrote againſt me, as touching the antient Sabbath, and the Lords-day Sabbath: as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe two I give this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> As touching the antient Sabbath, I do not endeavour punctually to confute any of his Anſwers made to <hi>divers</hi> of my twenty foure Arguments, left my books ſhould be cmmitted to the <hi>fire,</hi> and I ſhould offend
<pb facs="tcp:152852:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> the State: yet I have much ado to bridle my ſelfe ſo as to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in this quarrell: I only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to vindicate my ſelfe from Mr <hi>Cawdry's</hi> unfriendly abuſe of me, by <hi>fathering</hi> upon me the things I never wrote: and to <hi>vindicate</hi> God's fourth Commandement from his falſe Expoſitions of it; and my hope is, that the State will permit a man to do ſo much for <hi>God,</hi> and for <hi>himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> As for the Lords day <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> ſo called, but never ſo proved, I ſhall not here alleadge any Scriptures againſt it; nor confute any of Mr <hi>Cawdry's replies,</hi> made by him, to my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers which I made to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Texts of Scripture al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged for the Lords day, nor ſhall I need: for Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> hath rather replied to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers
<pb facs="tcp:152852:7"/> of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Ely,</hi> to Dr <hi>Heyline,</hi> and to Mr <hi>Prim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe,</hi> than to my anſwers: and yet he hath carried it on ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly, as his Reader cannot but thinke he hath confuted Mr <hi>Brabourne</hi> alſo, and this muſt go among the Vulgar for an Anſwer to my Books; this is one peece of Mr <hi>Cawdry's So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry:</hi> he cannot be content to abuſe me with fathering up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me falſely three Texts of <hi>Scripture:</hi> but alſo he muſt make the world beleeve that he hath anſwered my books againſt the <hi>Lords-day</hi> Sabbath, whereas he hath done no ſuch thing: he hath indeed menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned my name often, but never replied to my Anſwers: and if he hath mentioned any of them, inſtead of a Confutation he hath ſleightly paſſed by, and inſtead
<pb facs="tcp:152852:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> thereof he hath falne upon the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> Dr <hi>Heyline,</hi> or Mr. <hi>Primroſe;</hi> It is uſuall with moſt that write for the <hi>Lords day</hi> to have a fling at Mr <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bou ne;</hi> in one Page they among <hi>many</hi> things carpe at ſome one, and twenty or thirty Pages af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they carpe at another; and perhaps fifty or ſixty Pages after they carpe at a third, and ſo much for confutation of M. <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourne;</hi> thus have ſome done in their bookes from <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and many in their books in <hi>Old England;</hi> but none of them all <hi>dare</hi> undertake to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute all my Anſwers to their Texts: for I have given not only <hi>one</hi> Anſwer, but <hi>many</hi> Anſwers to <hi>every</hi> one of their Texts: So Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may ſtumble upon ſome <hi>one</hi> of my <hi>many</hi> Anſwers: but
<pb facs="tcp:152852:8"/> to go Text by Text, and confute all my Anſwers: anſwer by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as is meete and reaſonable, I have not yet ſeene it, nor do I beleeve that <hi>ever</hi> I ſhall ſee it: his wit in paſſing theſe things by in ſilence ſo ſleightly, is to me an Argument that he is at a <hi>non-plus,</hi> and therefore is faine to make a <hi>colour</hi> of an Anſwer, and to <hi>bluſter</hi> among the people with the <hi>wind</hi> of three great books: ſo thinks</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Theoph. Brabourne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152852:8"/>
            <head>Mr <hi>Brabourne's</hi> vindication of himſelfe from the unfriend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſe of Mr <hi>Cawdry,</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering upon him no leſs than three Texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and three Arguments deduced from them, to prove the morality or perpetuity of the antient ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>venth-day-Saturday-Sabbath, the which things M. <hi>Brabourne</hi> doth in no caſe own.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The words of Mr <hi>Cawdry.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SEE Mr <hi>Cawdries</hi> book on the Sabbath, his third part, in p. 429, 430. thus writing: <hi>Of all that have wrote of this ſubject</hi> (to wit the Sabbath day) <hi>Mr.</hi> Brabourne <hi>is the largeſt, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152852:9"/> hath the greateſt ſhew of Scripture and Reaſon for his opinion: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in confuting him we ſhall eaſily confute all the reſt; He hath produced five Texts of Scripture for himſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lfe, we conſider their ſtrength in order. Objection the firſt out of</hi> Gen. 2.3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt is taken from</hi> Gen. 2.3. <hi>whence thus he argueth: An Ordinance given in the ſtate of innocency, not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to that ſtate is perpetuall. But by divine inſtitution the ſeventh day was appointed to be the time of reſt in Innocency, and not appropriated to that ſtate. Ergo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this Text, and to this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deduced from it, I anſwer; At my firſt reading them my heart roſe againſt them, ſaying in my ſelfe, ſurely Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> hath done me wrong: then I tooke my firſt booke of the Sabbath, printed 1628. and ſought among my twelve Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments there for proofe of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity of the ancient ſeventh-day-Sabbath, but there I could not find theſe things; then I ſought in my ſecond book of the Sabbath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> printed 1632. among my twenty foure Arguments for the antient
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152852:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Sabbath, and there I could not find theſe things; Laſtly, becauſe I would make a through and full ſearch, I ſpent ſome houres to turne over both my books page by page, but neither ſo could I find theſe things; wherefore I diſclaime this firſt Text and Argument as none of mine.</p>
               <p>Mr <hi>Cawdry,</hi> in charging this, and two other Texts upon me, doth not ſay in which of my two books the Reader might find them; nor in which of my twelve or twenty foure Arguments theſe things may be found, nor in what page they may be found, ſo the Reader is left to ſeek a <hi>needle</hi> in a bottle of <hi>hay;</hi> there are 238. pages in my former booke, and 632. pages in my latter booke, ſo it is not eaſie for any man to find a thing without direction, but it is too common with ſome Writers, in a weake cauſe, wittily, I might ſay wickedly, to omit the quotation of the booke and page, and then to foiſt in what they pleaſe of their owne, the eaſilier to deceive the Reader, to abuſe the Author, and the better to gaine credit to their weake cauſe, by begetting a ſleighty opinion of their Adverſary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152852:10"/>
               <head>The ſecond Text.</head>
               <p>Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> in the place fore ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and page 430. thus writeth. <hi>Objection the ſecond. The ſecond place of Scripture is that of</hi> Exod. 31.16. <hi>where the Sabbath is call'd (An ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant) and therefore it is ſtill in force.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this Text, and the Argument deduced from it, I anſwer as before, that I have ſought for theſe things in my firſt booke, and in my twelve Arguments, and in my ſecond booke, and in my twenty foure Arguments there for the ſeventh-day. Sabbath: for where elſe ſhould I ſeeke but among my Arguments for this Text and Argument? But there I finde them not; yea, I have curſorily ſought page by page in both my books, but yet I cannot find them; wherefore I diſclaime them as none of mine.</p>
               <p>I yet remember, that before I printed my firſt book I had thoughts of this Text, <hi>Exod</hi> 31.16. where the Sabbath is called an <hi>Everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> but I then fore-ſaw that I could not from theſe words frame a ſound Argument to prove the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuity
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152852:10"/> of the ancient Sabbath, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Circumciſion</hi> is called an Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant alſo, wherefore I laid it aſide; and will Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> now father this weake Argument upon me? What can his end of it be but to render me, &amp; the cauſe I have in hand, ridiculous and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? To deceive his Reader? And to winne vaine applauſe to himſelfe and his cauſe?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The third Text.</head>
               <p>Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> in the place firſt cited, and in page 430. thus writeth; <hi>Objection the third from</hi> Iſa. 66.23. <hi>The third Text is</hi> Iſa. 66.23. <hi>where the Prophet, ſpeaking of the renewed ſtate of the Church by Chriſt, ſaith, from month to month, and Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath to Sabbath, all fleſh ſhould come to worſhip the Lord.</hi> To this Text he <hi>anſwereth,</hi> that the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and perpetuity of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bbath can no more be concluded hence than of the <hi>New Moons</hi> which are mentioned with the Sabbath, yet by himſelfe granted to be aboliſhed.</p>
               <p>I have ſought among my twelve Arguments in one of my books, and my twenty foure Arguments in my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152852:11"/> other booke, but cannot find any where that I alledged this text to prove the perpetuity of the ſeventh day-Saturday-Sabbath; wherefore I diſclaime this text alſo as none of mine, but of Mr <hi>Cawdry's</hi> own deviſing.</p>
               <p>As for his <hi>anſwer</hi> to it, doth Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> thinke Mr <hi>Brabourne</hi> ſo raſh in chooſing a Text to prove the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths perpetuity, as to make choice of this text, where the <hi>Sabbath</hi> is not preferred above the <hi>New Moons</hi> for perpetuity? But Mr <hi>Cawdry,</hi> it ſeems, knew no better way to bring Mr <hi>Brabourne</hi> into contempt with his Reader, than to forge ſuch ſhallow-brain'd things as this is, and then to father them upon Mr <hi>Brabourne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having ſpoken of the three texts ſeverally, now I ſhall ſpeake of them joyntly; Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> placeth theſe his, and not mine, three texts in the <hi>front,</hi> before my two texts which I owne (of which too by and by) here I note his ſophiſtry and carnall policy, hoping by the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of theſe three Texts, and my arguing ſo weakely from them, to bring me and my two texts follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152852:11"/> into a weake eſtimation with his Reader, that ſo he may thinke there is no more ſtrength of Argument in my two following texts, than is in the three texts going before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The fourth and fifth Texts.</head>
               <p>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> in page 431. thus writing: <hi>Objection the fourth. The fourth is taken out of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Mat. 5.17, 18. <hi>where our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ratifies the morall Law, the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue till the end of the world; whence thus he argueth: If every jot and tittle of the Law be in force untill the worlds end, then theſe letters and words, the ſeventh day is the Sabbath, are in force untill the worlds end. But the former is true by the Text alledged</hi> Mat. 5.17, 18. <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Objection the fifth. The laſt Text is</hi> Mat. 24.20. <hi>whence thus he argues: Their deſtruction was forty yeares after Chriſts death, yet he bids them pray that their flight might not be in the winter, nor on the Sabbath day; and therefore Chriſt foreſaw that the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day ſhould be in force ſtill, and kept after his death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe two texts indeed I own for mine, and the ſubſtance of the two
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152852:12"/> Arguments deduced from them, though but unhandſomly laid down by Mr <hi>Cawdry;</hi> now let the Reader judge whether there be not better force of proofe in theſe two texts than there was in the three texts ſet before them in the <hi>front,</hi> on purpoſe to diſgrace me and theſe two texts.</p>
               <p>As for the Text <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17, 18. I allow it as Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> hath laid it downe. As for the other text, <hi>Mat:</hi> 24.20. <hi>Pray that your flight be not on the Sabbath day;</hi> this flight was to be at the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> about fifty years after Chriſts death; whence I thus argue, that <hi>Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed</hi> of the antient Sabbath as a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Ordinance in the Church, all times of the Goſpell after his death; and had it been a dying <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony,</hi> as many fancy, Chriſt would not have bidden Chriſtians to pray to God to prevent their profanation of it, for this had been a profanation of the ſacred duty of Prayer; as if a Papiſt ſhould pray not to travell on Chriſtmas day.</p>
               <p>Having by theſe two Texts proved the <hi>perpetuity</hi> of the antient ſeventh day, and Saturday-Sabbath, it will
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152852:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> be expected by my Reader that I ſhould confute Mr <hi>Cawdry's anſwers</hi> to them; which thing I profeſſe I can eaſily doe without much ſtudy; but no provocations ſhall make me go beyond the bounds I have ſet to my ſelfe; I have reſolved to handle but two things: the one is to <hi>vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate</hi> my ſelfe from the abuſe of the three forged Texts: the other is to <hi>vindicate</hi> God's fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from Mr <hi>Cawdry's</hi> falſe gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and corrupt Expoſitions of it, ſaying, God commanded not the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day in <hi>order,</hi> but one day in the ſeven without <hi>order;</hi> and by this falſe Expoſition he makes his anſwer to many of my twenty foure Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>My hope is that as our <hi>State</hi> do allow <hi>liberty</hi> of Conſcience to ſome in ſome caſes, ſo they will allow me a <hi>liberty</hi> in theſe two things: firſt, to vindicate my ſelfe from ſlanders. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, to vindicate Gods fourth Commandement from falſe Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. I dare not go farther leſt I ſhould offend the <hi>State,</hi> and have my books burnt; one Mr <hi>Ockford</hi> about two yeares paſt wrote a booke
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152852:13"/> in defence of my way againſt the Lords day, and for the old day the ſeventh day, but, as ſaith Mr <hi>Cawdry,</hi> it was anſwered by <hi>fire,</hi> being orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be burnt; as I remember Mr <hi>Tyndals</hi> Tranſlation of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament long ſince was ordered to be burnt too; and was not <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eus</hi> on the <hi>Romans</hi> burnt alſo in King <hi>James</hi> his daies? And I feare me ſo it would be with this my book if I ſhould exceed my bounds; Let not therefore Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> thinke, that I do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to his anſwers becauſe I cannot, but becauſe I dare not; if I durſt, and had but this faire dealing, to have the Preſſe as open to me as it is to him, he ſhould ſoone ſee that I would make his weakneſſe in argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to appeare unto all men. I had rather be engaged in this quarrell than go to my dinner or ſupper. When two Souldiers are to fight, the odds is too great, to give al en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements and conveniences to the one, and bind the hands of the other behind him, or hold a cudgell over his head if he ſtrikes a blow; it is my unhappy condition to ſuffer this odds, to have the fire prepared
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152852:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> for my books, and the benefit of the Preſſe denied me, unleſſe I Print by ſtealth. So far for vindication of my ſelfe: and now for the vindication of the fourth Commandement.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the vindication of Gods fourth Commandement.</head>
                  <p>Before I fall cloſe upon this point, I ſhall premiſe five things tending to the vindication of this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What may be the reaſon of Mr <hi>Cawdry's</hi> wreſting theſe words in the fourth Commandement; <hi>The ſeventh day is the Sabbath,</hi> from the proper ſenſe of the <hi>ordinall</hi> number ſeventh? which ſignifies not only one of ſeven, but more, as the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt of ſeven, and that ſingle one which followes the ſixe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies labour; and why would he inſtead of this bring in <hi>one day of ſeven indefinitely?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>His tacite reaſon I beleeve is this, that having no <hi>precept</hi> for the <hi>Lords day</hi> in the <hi>New</hi> Teſtament, and none but poore probable reaſons <hi>ab ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplo,</hi> therefore he would faine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate the Lords day into the fourth Commandement to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then it: ſo it having no legs of its
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152852:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> own to ſtand on, he would be ſo friendly to it, as to borrow a paire of legs from the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then it ſhall be able to ſtand in the opinion of the deluded multitude. As for his Arguments <hi>ab exemplo,</hi> from <hi>example,</hi> as is the <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed practice</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> however it go current in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> yet Sir, if you know it not, let me informe you, that an Argument <hi>ab exemplo</hi> in <hi>Diſputation</hi> is next unto nothing, try it when you will.</p>
                  <p>For my part, if it could be proved that the <hi>Lords day</hi> had a <hi>divine</hi> inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, which I never ſaw proved, nor hath Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> proved it in any or all of his three larger Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes on the Sabbath; I ſay, if it could be proved to be ſet up by Chriſt or his Apoſtles, yet I <hi>ſtiffely deny it</hi> to be commanded in the fourth Commandement, for the Lords day is called in Scr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ure the <hi>firſt</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y of the weeke, but the fourth Commandement is f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r the ſeventh and <hi>laſt</hi> day of the weeke; and the Lords day was not <hi>known</hi> when the fourth Commandement was given on mount <hi>Sinai.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152852:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>If, as you ſay, <hi>Chriſt</hi> did inſtitute the Lords day, is not Chriſts <hi>inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and authority ſufficient for it, but that you muſt run unto the Old Teſtament, the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for a Law and Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for it? Chriſt hath inſtituted two new Sacraments, <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper;</hi> now, is not Chriſts inſtitution and authority ſufficient to uphold them, but that we muſt run to the Old Teſtament as unto the Laws and Commandements for <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and the <hi>Paſſeover?</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, our two Sacraments ſtand by force of the two Laws in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. So if Chriſt had ſet up a <hi>third</hi> new Ordinance, as the <hi>Lords day,</hi> what need we to run further than the New Teſtament, and then to <hi>Chriſts</hi> inſtitution and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for it.</p>
                  <p>But you will ſay, Circumciſion and the Paſſeover are Ceremonials, but the fourth Commandement is Morall. I anſwer, if the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement be <hi>morall,</hi> then the <hi>time</hi> there commanded is morall too: and morall things are not alterable: <hi>one jot or tittle ſhall not paſſe from the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152852:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> Law</hi> ſo long as heaven and earth laſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18.</p>
                  <p>It is a ſigne the cauſe is naught, when the Authors of it are ſo put to their ſhifts, and to uſe their wits, as to run ſuch ſtrange and unuſuall cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as to run from the <hi>New</hi> Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament, and that for a <hi>new Ordinance:</hi> yea, and alſo to wreſt the proper ſenſe of the fourth Commandement, as if it were a <hi>noſe</hi> of wax, to be bowed on this ſide at one time, and on the other ſide at another time: to command the <hi>Saturday</hi> for thouſands of years untill Chriſt, and the <hi>Sunday,</hi> or Lords day for ever after Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. I ſhall premiſe another thing, which is a <hi>diſtinction</hi> of Mr <hi>Cawdries,</hi> ſaying, in his ſecond part, page 255. The old world had the <hi>laſt</hi> day of the weeke, the new world the <hi>firſt</hi> day of the weeke. Now by the old world he meanes the Church of the Jews before Chriſt, and by the new world the Chriſtian Church ſince Chriſt; and both theſe have their <hi>ſeverall daies</hi> from this <hi>one</hi> fourth Commandement; now this is a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> diſtinction in its application:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152852:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> for Papiſts ſay of the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, that it forbade <hi>Images</hi> indeed to the <hi>Jews,</hi> that is, to the old world, but not unto <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that is, to the new world: and ſo ſaith Mr <hi>Cawdry,</hi> the fourth Commandement was for the <hi>laſt</hi> day of the weeke to the Jews of the old world, but it is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t ſo to Chriſtians of the new world, for it commands us the <hi>firſt</hi> day of the weeke; might he not as well ſay, Proteſtants are bound by the fifth Commandement to honour their <hi>Parents;</hi> and by the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement Papiſts are bound to honour the <hi>Pope,</hi> but not their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents? Never did Jeſuites more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the ſecond Commandement, than Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> doth the fourth Commandement.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. I ſhall premiſe this alſo; that Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> ſaith in his ſecond part, page 255. That the ſeventh day in order was not the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the fourth Commandement. In his third part, page 418. He ſaith, The ground of all the <hi>Sabbatarian errour</hi> is, that they take for granted, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth-day-Saturday-Sabbath was commanded as the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152852:16"/> fourth Commandement; we agree with them in this, that if it be ſo we muſt turne <hi>Anabaptiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> who keep no day, or <hi>Sabbatarians,</hi> to keep the ſeventh day with the Jews; but this is their miſtake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in p. 259. of his ſecond part he ſaith, one day in ſeven is the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the fourth Commandement.</p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer, Firſt, if theſe words, <hi>The ſeventh day is the Sabbath,</hi> be not the ſubſtance of the fourth Commandement, how can <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> words, <hi>one day in ſeven,</hi> be the ſubſtance of the Commandement? Are they not both ſpoken of the <hi>time?</hi> If the one be the ſubſtance, then the other i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a ſubſtance alſo; and if that which is not expreſſed in the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as one day in ſeven, be the ſubſtance of it, then much rather muſt theſe words, the ſeventh day, which are expreſſed in the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, be the ſubſtance of the Commandement.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For this word <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> it is not uſed here <hi>properly;</hi> for it hath neither <hi>Circumſtance</hi> nor <hi>Accident</hi> in the fourth Commadement; the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is the duty of <hi>reſt</hi> from la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152852:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> and the <hi>worſhip</hi> of God; the <hi>time</hi> is the Circumſtance. Beſides, few Readers underſtand what ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and accident are; wherefore I would require Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare this word ſubſtance, and ſtate the queſtion by ſome other word which is proper, and which every Reader may underſtand, as to uſe the word <hi>commanded;</hi> for we ſpeake of one of Gods Commandements, and of a day or time commanded; which alſo will avoid ſtrife betweene the diſputants about the word ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, it being liable to be uſed ſometime in one ſenſe, ſometime in another; Now, if you uſe the word commanded, then Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> muſt ſay, The ſeventh day was not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, but one day of ſeven was commanded; both which are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lſe: for <hi>the ſeventh day</hi> was expreſly commanded in ſo many words, ſaying, <hi>The ſeventh day is the Sabbath, in it thou ſhalt not do any worke;</hi> but <hi>one day of ſeven</hi> was not commanded or expreſſed in the fourth Commandement; So now <hi>Sir,</hi> they are your own words, you muſt turn <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> keeping no day, or
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152852:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>Sabbatarian,</hi> keeping the Saturday-Sabbath with the Jews, now take your choice,</p>
                  <p n="4">4. I ſhall premiſe this alſo; Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> ſaith in his ſecond part, page 257. In <hi>like manner</hi> we ſuppoſe it may be ſaid, that the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement ſaith, Thou ſhalt ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie one day of ſeven <hi>at Gods appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that is, in particular, God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the laſt day of ſeven to the old world, and the firſt day of ſeven to the new world.</p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer; H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re he makes <hi>one day of ſeven</hi> to be the <hi>genus,</hi> whereas thoſe words be no where ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt in the fourth Commandement, nor are gatherable by conſequence; and then he makes the <hi>laſt</hi> day of ſeven, the Saturday, and the <hi>fi ſt</hi> day of ſeven, the Sunday to be the two <hi>ſpecies;</hi> the former appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God to the Jews in the fourth Commandement, the latter appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God to Chriſtians in or by the fourth Commandement alſo; but is it not ſtrange, that</p>
                  <p n="1">1. God ſhould appoint two ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s by one ſingle Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and never to expreſſe any
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152852:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> more than <hi>one?</hi> For the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement mentions but one day <hi>ſingularly,</hi> not daies <hi>plurally;</hi> as the Sabbath day, not daies: and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, not daies, <hi>Exod.</hi> 10 8, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Is it not ſtrange, that in one and the ſame Commandement, and in the very ſame words, God ſhould appoint both a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Sabbath? And the one to be kept in memory of the <hi>Creation,</hi> the other of the <hi>Redemption?</hi> But ſuch things are nothing ſtrange to Mr <hi>Cawdry.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Is it not ſtrange, that God ſhould appoint to the Jews their <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth-day-Sabbath</hi> at the giving of the Law on mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and at the ſame time, and in the ſame words, without any difference making, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the <hi>Lords day</hi> to <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> a day not known then to the Jews, nor to have any being or beginning, for thouſands of yeares after, till Chriſt came? This <hi>Lords day</hi> was hidden ſo ſecretly in the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that had not Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> ſtept up of late, by his more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wit and skill in Logick, to ſearch and find it out for us in the fourth Commandement, we ſhould never
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152852:18"/> have thought of ſuch a Jewell lockt up in the fourth Commandement; I marvell he hath not found alſo the Sacrament of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> to be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God in <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly lockt up in the old Law for Circumciſion: and our <hi>Lords Supper</hi> to be appointed by G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d for us Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> and cloſely hidden in the old Law for the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, and then, and <hi>there</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to us; though theſe were cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, yet our Chriſtian Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in them might be morall or perpetuall.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Is it not ſtrange, that <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpell</hi> both ſhould be comprized in <hi>one</hi> Commandement, and in one and the ſame words without any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence made by God? Did God want words that he muſt expreſſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring things in one and the ſame word? had not Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> found out this myſtery, I muſt profeſſe, I ſhould have been deeply ignorant of it; now, the old Sabbath day was <hi>Law,</hi> and a part of the Law and Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue: and the feigned Lords day in the fourth Commandement was <hi>Goſpell,</hi> it being kept in memory of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152852:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> our Redemption by Chriſt; ſo there was both Law and Goſpell comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God in the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, according to Mr <hi>Cawdry;</hi> theſe things conſidered, is not Gods fourth Commandement ſhamefully abuſed by Mr <hi>Cawdry?</hi> and is it not high time to vindicate it?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. I ſhall premiſe another thing; Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> in his ſecond part, page the 255, 257, 256, 265. ſaith, that one day in ſeven is <hi>directly</hi> commanded in the fourth Commandement; but the ſeventh day is <hi>indirectly</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; now I ſuppoſe that is ſaid to be directly which is <hi>expreſſed</hi> in words; and that indirectly which is <hi>gathered</hi> from the words by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of reaſon, and ſo Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> underſtands it, ſaying in page 255. <hi>expreſly</hi> and <hi>directly,</hi> both words of the ſame ſenſe; and in Page 259. not directly but by conſequence.</p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer; Is it not ſtrange Sir, that you ſhould ſay, <hi>one day of ſeven</hi> is directly commanded, when theſe words, one day in ſeven, are not to be found in the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement? And to ſay theſe words
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152852:19"/> 
                     <hi>The ſeventh day,</hi> which are expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, are but indirectly, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence commanded? Surely, if any thing be indirectly in the fourth Commandement it muſt be one in ſeven, becauſe theſe words are not in the Commandement. In the fifth Commandement the thing directly and expreſly commanded is, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our naturall Parents: but to honour Magiſtrates is indirectly, and by conſequence commanded, it not being expreſſed; why you ſhould ſo croſſe a received diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeems a Paradox to me.</p>
                  <p>Theſe five things I have premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and now I come a little cloſer to the worke, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Cawdry</hi> leads me on: and thus he begins to defend <hi>One day in ſeven</hi> to be the true ſenſe and meaning of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and that it is no <hi>para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxall</hi> expoſition of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To hold one day of ſeven is the ſenſe of the fourth Commandement is not a Paradox.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His firſt inſtance.</head>
               <p>Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> in his ſecond part, p. 257. gives for inſtance the <hi>place</hi> of Gods worſhip, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.5, 11. where
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152852:19"/> it is ſaid to this effect: <hi>Ye ſhall offer all your ſacrifices only in the place which the Lord ſhall chooſe;</hi> and the place choſen by God afterward, was firſt the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> and after it the <hi>Temple;</hi> now it is evident that this precept did not enjoyne them direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to offer their Sacrifices at the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle; or at the Temple, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indirectly. <hi>In like manner</hi> it may be ſaid of the <hi>time</hi> of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; the fourth Commandement ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſanctifie one day of ſeven at Gods appointment,</hi> as the <hi>laſt</hi> day of ſeven to the old world, and the <hi>firſt</hi> day of ſeven to the new world, but neither of them directly by the fourth Commandement, but indirectly.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer. 1. Theſe caſes are not <hi>alike:</hi> for as touching the <hi>place</hi> of Gods worſhip, <hi>Deut</hi> 12. it was commanded only in <hi>generall</hi> or <hi>ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>finitely,</hi> not naming any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular place; and ſo both Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle and Temple were indirectly commanded as by conſequence; but as for the <hi>time</hi> of Gods worſhip, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.8, &amp;c. it was not comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in generall or indefinitely, but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152852:20"/> in <hi>particular</hi> and <hi>definitely,</hi> naming <hi>the ſeventh day</hi> the particular and definite time; and this is not indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly, but directly and expreſly commanded.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The caſes are <hi>unlike</hi> in this, that as for the place of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, after God had indefinitely commanded it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. it was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently known to be afterwards the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and the <hi>Temple,</hi> no man queſtioning it; but as for the <hi>Lords day,</hi> or firſt day of the new world, conſidered as a Sabbath of divine inſtitution, hath been denied by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny learned and godly <hi>Divines,</hi> whoſe names and <hi>words</hi> I have mentioned in my ſecond booke of the Sabbath, Pag. 264, &amp;c. as <hi>Peter Martyr, Bren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Calvin, Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nchie, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus, Pare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Chemnitius, Dr. Prideaux, Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inglius, Melanchton, Hemingius, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingius,</hi> Mr <hi>Tindall,</hi> and Mr <hi>Fryth</hi> two godly <hi>Martyrs</hi> with others there named, and many more I could name, if it were needfull, all of them holding and writing that the <hi>Lords day</hi> is but an <hi>indifferent</hi> thing, and of the ſame authority with <hi>Chriſtmas day,</hi> St <hi>Mathews day,</hi> and the other
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152852:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Holy daies</hi> of the Church; To theſe I may adde that ſince I wrote my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond booke of the Sabbath, I have ſeene neere twenty <hi>books</hi> lately prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all againſt the <hi>Lords-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ſo it is not ſo clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a caſe among us that the Lords day, the firſt day of the wee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, or the firſt day o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the new world, is appointed by God, for the <hi>time</hi> of Gods worſhip, as it was cleare to the Jews, that the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle or Temple was appointed of God for the <hi>place</hi> of his worſhip; yea, at this day among our ſelves it is a controverſie to know which d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y is the Sabbath day, the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>turday or the Sunday.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whereas you ſay Sir, The fourth Commandement ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſanctifie one day of ſeven.</hi> This is falſe: if no man had the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements but your ſelfe, you might ſay what you liſt, as you do; but being all men have them as well as your ſelfe, no man will beleeve you ſo long as they read no ſuch words in the Commandements: or if you take it for <hi>granted</hi> before you have <hi>proved</hi> it, as here you do, that your wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds are the <hi>ſence</hi> and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152852:21"/> of the fourth Commandement, then you do but ſophiſtically beg the queſtion.</p>
               <p>Thus you have ſeen that this firſt inſtance proves nothing; for it ſhews not that one day of ſeven may be the ſenſe and meaning of the fourth Commandement, nor that you, Sir, are freed from a <hi>Paradox</hi> in ſaying the fourth Commandement enjoynes one day of ſeven.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His ſecond inſtance.</head>
               <p>Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> in page 258. thus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth; We ſhall give light to our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion by comparing the <hi>time</hi> of worſhip, and the worſhip it <hi>ſelfe:</hi> comparing the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the ſecond Commandement doth not <hi>directlly</hi> and expreſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the <hi>particular ſervices,</hi> as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, Circumciſion, the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet all theſe fall under the generall Obligation of the ſecond Commandement by way of <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,</hi> as <hi>ſpeciales</hi> to a generall: The like may be ſaid of the ſervices of the New Teſtament <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> &amp;c. and theſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices are reduced to the generall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152852:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> morality of the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; juſt ſo (we thinke) it is in the fourth Commandement; the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all day, the ſeventh day, was not <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly</hi> and expreſly commanded in the fourth Commandement, no, nor the Lords day, yet both fell under the Obligation of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement as <hi>ſpecials</hi> to a <hi>generall.</hi> To this I anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Suppoſing, but not granting, that Sacrifices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper were commanded in the generall in the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, yet the Saturday-ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth-day-Sabbath, and the Lords day were not both commanded in the <hi>generall</hi> in the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Lords day</hi> it was not <hi>thought</hi> on at the giving of the Law on mount <hi>Sinai</hi> in the wilderneſſe, how ſhould it then be commanded in the fourth Commandement? Nor can it be <hi>underſtood</hi> in the fourth Commandement, for this is for the day called by its proper name (as ſhall hereafter appeare) Sabbath day; <hi>Remember the Sabbath day,</hi> now the fourth Commandement binds to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152852:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> Saturday, properly called Sabbath day, cannot bind to Sunday, or Lords day, the day following.</p>
               <p>Againe the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſaith, <hi>The ſeventh day is the Sabbath,</hi> which is Saturday the <hi>laſt</hi> day of the weeke, but the Lords day is Sunday the <hi>firſt</hi> day, and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the weeke following; now how ſhould a <hi>bond</hi> of one hundred pound to be paid on the ſeven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h day of <hi>May</hi> be underſtood to bind to the day following the eighth day of <hi>May</hi> without a forfeiture of the Bond? Or a bond to be paid on Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday the ſeventh day of the week, but to be forfeited if it be not paid till Sunday after the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt day of the next weeke? When the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement binds to the ſeventh and <hi>laſt</hi> day of the weeke, it cannot bind to the <hi>firſt</hi> day of the weeke, the Lords day; ſo you ſee that the Lords day was not commanded in the fourth Commandement in the <hi>generall,</hi> no more than in the particular.</p>
               <p>Now as for the Saturday-ſeventh-day-Sabbath, this indeed was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but not <hi>generally,</hi> as is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152852:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> comprizing under it Saturday and Sunday, both as ſpecialls: for Saturday the ſeventh day was no generall but a ſpeciall, ſingle, and individuall day, as is granted me, But I ſuppoſe Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands his <hi>one day in ſeven</hi> to be the generall, and Saturday and Sunday the ſpecialls; but to expound the fourth Commandement of one day in ſeven is a falſe Expoſition, and as yet Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> hath not proved it to be the ſenſe and meaning of the fourth Commandement; yet here and before he takes it for granted, and ſuppoſeth one day of ſeven to be the <hi>genus</hi> or general of the fourth Commandement; but this his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is but <hi>petitio principii,</hi> a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the queſtion of me before he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h proved it.</p>
               <p>Thus you have ſeene by my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> hath not by his ſecond inſtance vindicated himſelfe from this <hi>Paradoxe</hi> in expounding the fourth Commandement for one day of ſeven; nor hath he proved that the fourth Commandement may be expounded for one day of ſeven.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:152852:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>2. Whereas Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> makes Sacrifices, and the Paſſeover, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and the Lords Supper to be ſpecialls, under the generall Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what doth he but <hi>mingle</hi> Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonials with Morals? And ſo <hi>confound</hi> the morall and the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Laws; making Sacrifices, Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and Paſſeover to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the morall Law, as in the ſecond Commandement? methinks Sir, it beſeemes not a <hi>Divine</hi> of your ranke thus to <hi>jumble</hi> together Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals and Ceremonials. 2 Sacrifices and the Paſſover were <hi>Goſpell,</hi> I ſay. Goſpel <hi>vailed</hi> under ſhadows, typing out Chriſt; Baptiſme and the Lords Supper are Goſpell alſo, pointing to Chriſt; now Sir, will you mingle <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſpell</hi> together? Saying, Sacrifices, and the Paſſeover, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and the Lords Supper fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Obligation</hi> of the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement? Will you confound Law and Goſpell? for the ſecond Commandement is Law, and a part of the morall Law; now to thruſt theſe Evangelicall things into the ſecond Commandement, is to jumble
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152852:23"/> together the Law and the Goſpell; I confeſſe, you may as well thruſt and crowd the <hi>Lords day</hi> into the fourth Commandement as you may crowd <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> into the ſecond Commandement, but both are but <hi>Carter-like</hi> done.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whereas Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and in two or three paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his before, makes the Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and the Sunday or Lords day to be <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or ſpecialls under the <hi>genus</hi> or generall of <hi>one day in ſeven</hi> in the fourth Commandement; how can he make this <hi>Logicke</hi> good? Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we that his <hi>one day of ſeven</hi> were the <hi>genus,</hi> ſince all <hi>Logicians</hi> know that the <hi>genus</hi> muſt have <hi>two ſpecies</hi> at leaſt, theſe two daies can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the <hi>ſpecies:</hi> for during the old world, as he cals it, untill <hi>Chriſt</hi> the fourth Commandement, under one day of ſeven, had but <hi>one ſpecies,</hi> namely, the Saturday-ſeventh-day-Sabbath as himſelf confeſſeth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and ſince <hi>Chriſt,</hi> if the Lords day be a Sabbath, as he ſaies, and be alſo <hi>packt,</hi> or <hi>patcht,</hi> I may rather ſay, into the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet then from Chriſts time un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152852:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> our times there hath been but one <hi>ſpecies</hi> under his <hi>genus,</hi> of one day in ſeven in the fourth Commandement, as the Sunday or Lords day; now, how can Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> make his one day of ſeven to be a <hi>genus,</hi> when it ever wanted two <hi>ſpecies?</hi> As both before Chriſt, and ſince Chriſt; his <hi>divinity,</hi> in expounding the fourth Commandement for one day of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, is like his <hi>Logick</hi> in making a <hi>genus</hi> to ſubſiſt with but one ſingle <hi>ſpecies.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His third inſtance.</head>
               <p>Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> in page 260. thus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth; in <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.30. <hi>All the tithes or tenths of the land are the Lords,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The tenth of the Flocks which paſſeth under the rod ſhall be the Lords;</hi> Where it is not neceſſary to take it for the tenth in <hi>order,</hi> but for any part of the ten. Alſo <hi>Lev.</hi> 23.13. <hi>Two tenth deales of flower, and a fourth part of an hin of oyle;</hi> here any part of the ten, or any part of the foure is as much as this Law requires. So the ſeventh day mentioned in the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement doth not neceſſarily ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the ſeventh day in <hi>order,</hi> but may ſignifie <hi>a</hi> ſeventh day, or <hi>one</hi> day
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152852:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the ſeven. So this is ſufficient to take off the aſperſion of <hi>novelty</hi> from our interpretation and expoſition of the fourth Commandement, and to ſhew it to be conſonant to the <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> of the Scripture.</p>
               <p>To this I ſay, whereas in expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the fourth Commandement I do inſiſt upon the <hi>ordinall</hi> word <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth,</hi> holding my ſelfe cloſe to the <hi>propriety</hi> of it, which notifies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly (as hereafter ſhall appeare) not any one of the ſeven, but the laſt of the ſeven, and that ſingle one which next follows the ſixth. As when we ſay, the ſeventh yeare of the <hi>Kings</hi> Reigne, we meane not <hi>one of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> indefinitely, that is, any one of the ſeven, but the laſt yeare of the ſeven, that which follows next after his ſixth yeares Raigne. A <hi>bond</hi> to be paid the ſeventh day of <hi>March</hi> is not to be paid upon <hi>one of the ſeven daies</hi> of <hi>March</hi> indefinitely, that is, upon any one day of the ſeven, but defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely upon the ſeventh day from the firſt day of <hi>March;</hi> the like may be ſaid of the eighth day for <hi>Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and of the fourteenth day for the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> and of other ordinall
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152852:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> numbers which in our Engliſh tongue end with <hi>th.</hi> Now Mr <hi>Caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry,</hi> to overthrow this propriety of the <hi>ordinall</hi> number ſeventh, brings in this his inſtance of another <hi>ordinall</hi> number, the tythe, or tenth. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whereas Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by the <hi>Tythe</hi> or tenth, not the tenth in order, but for any one of the ten indefinitely; hereby as he would overturne Gods definite and fixed time, ſo he doth an evill office to himſelfe, and to the reſt of the <hi>Clergy</hi> for matter of <hi>Tythes;</hi> for if the Shepheard hath in his Flock a blind or lame Lambe, a ſick or leane Lambe, may he not give the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter for tythe his blind Lambe, ſick or leane Lambe? And if the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter thinks himſelfe wronged, may not the <hi>Shepheard</hi> plead <hi>Scripture</hi> to him? Saying, by the tythe or tenth God might enjoyne <hi>one of ten,</hi> that is, any one of the ten indefinitely. Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> would be loath the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheard ſhould ſo expound <hi>Scripture</hi> to him, and yet he will ſo expound the fourth Commandement to us, underſtanding by the ſeventh day
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152852:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> any one day of the ſeven.</p>
               <p>Againe, God commanded <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion</hi> to be on the eighth; were Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> to expound this Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he could ſay by the eighth day may be underſtood any <hi>one of the eight daies.</hi> The <hi>Paſſeover</hi> on the fourteenth day, he could expound this ordinall fourteenth ſo, as they might eate it on any <hi>one of the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene daies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Though there is not any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement in the New Teſtament for the <hi>Lords day,</hi> yet let us ſuppoſe one made by Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Lords day to ſanctifie it; but the firſt day of the weeke is the Lords day,</hi> &amp;c. If I ſhould anſwer to this Commandement as Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> doth to Gods fourth Commandement, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the word <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt</hi> is an <hi>ordinall</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber indeed, but by the firſt day of the weeke, or firſt day of the ſeven, we may underſtand one day of the week, or one day of the ſeven indefinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; for ordinall numbers, as the tenth of the Flock, and a tenth deale of flower, are ſo uſed in Scripture; how would Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> and our new <hi>Sabbatarians</hi> exclaime of me for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152852:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> the proper ſence of this new Commandement of <hi>Chriſts?</hi> and for beguiling them of their <hi>new Sabbath day?</hi> And yet thus they deale with <hi>God,</hi> and with his fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and no man may controul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them without ſome heavy <hi>Cenſure</hi> or other, for I run more hazard for maintaining the true expoſition of Gods Commandement than they do for corrupting it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Be it ſo, that ſome few, as two or three ordinall numbers in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be uſed improperly: for <hi>Io.</hi> 21.14. <hi>This is the third time that Jeſus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare,</hi> &amp;c. if this <hi>third</hi> time of Chriſts <hi>apparition</hi> may be upon ſome one of the three times only, and not on the laſt of the three, how ſhall we do for our new <hi>Sabbath</hi> on the <hi>Lords day?</hi> for Chriſts <hi>apparitions</hi> be brought to prove our new Sabbath. Againe, <hi>Chriſt</hi> roſe the <hi>third</hi> day, may this be expounded of, one of, or of any of the three daies? further I anſwer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That this <hi>particular</hi> ordinall number <hi>the ſeventh</hi> mentioned in the fourth Commandement, is never uſed in Scripture but properly for the laſt of ſeven. As for o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152852:26"/> numbers, ſome two or three, as the tenth of the Flock, and a fourth part of a hin of oyle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe are uſed <hi>improperly,</hi> but there are an hundred Texts of ordinalls, all uſed properly for one or two uſed impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Where an ordinall number is uſed improperly, it is ſo underſtood in a caſe of <hi>neceſſity</hi> only, when it cannot poſſibly be otherwiſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; as when the things numbred have in them neither <hi>diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rence,</hi> nor <hi>order,</hi> as a fourth part of an hin of oyle, and a tenth deale of flower; in ſuch a caſe we muſt underſtand them improperly as for any one of the number: ſo when <hi>Chriſt</hi> is called a <hi>doo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> and the <hi>bread</hi> his <hi>body,</hi> we muſt take them improperly, but not alwaies in all texts ſo: for the proper ſenſe is ever holden for the true ſenſe, if nothing appeare to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; now there is no <hi>neceſſity</hi> to depart from the proper ſenſe of the ordinall ſeventh in the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement; for among the ſeven daies there is both <hi>difference</hi> and <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> one orderly going after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; wherefore this ordinall ſeventh
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152852:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> muſt be <hi>properly</hi> underſtood for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday the laſt of ſeven; and ſo the <hi>Church</hi> of the Jews underſtood it, as appeares by their practice, keeping the Saturday Sabbath, now at <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> and elſewhere; but this I ſhall at our concluſion more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly prove, as that God intended in his fourth Commandement to have only the Saturday and laſt day of ſeven definitely for his Sabbath.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee his third and laſt inſtance anſwered; and as yet he hath not vindicated himſelfe from his <hi>Paradoxe,</hi> nor proved that the fourth Commandement may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for a ſeventh day, or for one day of ſeven indefinitely, that is, for any one day of the ſeven.</p>
               <p>By the way note, that I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded his three <hi>inſtances</hi> in their <hi>full ſtrength,</hi> as himſelfe wrote them; the like faithfulneſſe I ſhall obſerve in repeating his enſuing <hi>Arguments;</hi> And though they be but triviall things, yet I have, and ſhall anſwer every one of them punctually, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he hath not been ſo candid towards me; for he hath not ſo much as <hi>mentioned,</hi> much leſſe confuted my
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152852:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>beſt anſwers</hi> againſt the <hi>Lords day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> if my things were as triviall as his, yet ſince he undertakes to confute me, it had been the part of a fair diſputant to mention and confute my anſwers, or elſe never to meddle with my <hi>name</hi> and <hi>Books,</hi> and ſo I returne.</p>
               <p>Now he proceeds by ſundry <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments</hi> that the ſeventh day, or laſt day of the ſeven, is not enjoyned in the fourth Commandement, but one day of the ſeven indefinitely; we ſhall anſwer them in order.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His firſt Argument.</head>
               <p>Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> in his ſecond part, page 261. thus reaſoneth: <hi>If the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the day (firſt or laſt) in the fourth Commandement be not ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially profitable, or being altered is no waies prejudiciall to Religion, then the ſeventh day was not commanded as the ſubject or ſubſtance of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the order of the day, (firſt, or laſt, or any other) is not ſubſtantially profitable; or being altered is it any waies prejudiciall to Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore the ſeventh day in order
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152852:28"/> was not commanded as the ſubject or ſubſtance of the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer firſt to the firſt propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to the conſequent part of it, ſaying, Then the ſeventh day was not commanded as the <hi>ſubject</hi> or <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of the fourth Commandement; To this I ſay, the ſeventh day is <hi>time</hi> and <hi>order;</hi> now time and order are neither <hi>ſubject</hi> nor <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> but <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct, accident,</hi> or <hi>circumſtance;</hi> now if I ſhould grant your <hi>concluſion,</hi> what were I the worſe, or you the better by this Argument? For though the ſeventh day be not commanded as the ſubject or ſubſtance, yet if it be <hi>commanded</hi> as an adjunct to the duty of holineſſe, or Gods worſhip, or as an accident or circumſtance, it is <hi>binding</hi> to obedience: for it is a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded</hi> adjunct, accident, or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</p>
               <p>I anſwer now to the ſecond pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and to the former part of it, ſaying, The order of the day, as the laſt day of ſeven, is not <hi>ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially profitable:</hi> To this I ſay, 1. What if it be not <hi>ſubſtantially</hi> profitable, if it be <hi>circumſtantially profitable?</hi> Is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152852:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> not this as much as can be expected of a commanded <hi>time?</hi> furthermore, if one day of ſeven, that is, any one of ſeven, be ſubſtantially profitable, as you Sir ſay, why ſhould not the ſeventh and laſt day of the ſeven be alſo ſubſtantially profitable? Is not the ſeventh day one day of the ſeven?</p>
               <p>I anſwer next to the latter part, ſaying, The ſeventh day being <hi>alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> it is not any waies <hi>prejudiciall</hi> to Religion. To this I ſay, 1. If this alteration be not prejudiciall to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that is, to Gods worſhip in the day, yet it is prejudiciall to <hi>God,</hi> and to his fourth Commandement; for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it not prejudiciall to God to have his <hi>holy day,</hi> and the day cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by him before all other daies of the ſeven, to be altered and changed, and ſo <hi>rejected?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, ſuppoſe the alteration of the ſeventh day be no <hi>dammage</hi> to Religion and Gods worſhip in the day; ſo ſay I, the taking up of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other day for it, as the Lords day, the firſt day of the weeke, this is no <hi>gaine</hi> or advantage to Religion and Gods worſhip; now will any wiſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152852:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> man make a change of any thing if it be not for a <hi>better?</hi> It is the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t of a foole to change one Penny for another, or one Counter for another, both being alike. Furthermore, the alteration of the ſeventh day is as prejudiciall to Religion, as the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of the firſt day is advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Religion; and therefore the ſeventh day may be as well the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Commandement as the firſt day.</p>
               <p>Againe, is it not prejudiciall to change the ſeventh day, which hath a divine inſtitution and <hi>precept</hi> for it, and Gods <hi>example</hi> in reſting on that day, for the Lords day, or firſt day, which hath no divine inſtitution or <hi>precept</hi> for it, nor Chriſts <hi>example</hi> in reſting on this day? For Chriſt made the <hi>Lords day</hi> a travelling day, and ſo did two of his Diſciples, travelling ſixty <hi>furlongs</hi> to <hi>Emmaus,</hi> and back againe to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which is fifteene miles, eight Furlongs to a mile, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.1, 23, 29, 33. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.19. this is more than a Sabbath daies jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
               <p>To conclude, give me leave Sir, to retort your Argument againſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152852:29"/> your ſelfe on this manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If one day of ſeven indefinitely be not ſubſtantially profitable: or being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered is no way prejudiciall to Religion; then one day of ſeven was not comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as the ſubject or ſubſtance of the fourth Commandement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But one of ſeven indefinitely is not ſubſtantially profitable: or being alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the ſeventh day definitely, it is no way prejudiciall to Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore one day of ſeven was not commanded as the ſubject or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the fourth Commandement.</hi> My anſwers to his Argument will cleare this Argument; ſo far of his firſt Argument.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His ſecond Argument.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the ſeventh day was directly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded as the ſubject or ſubſtance of the fourth Commandement, then it was commanded as Ceremoniall, or as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the ſeventh day was neither commanded as Ceremoniall, nor as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Therefore the ſeventh day was not commanded at all in the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:152852:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>I have heard Country people ſay, Schollers can by Logick prove the Moone was made of a greene cheeſe; now is not Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> ſuch a Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian? for his concluſion ſaith, <hi>The ſeventh day was not commanded at all in the fourth Commandement,</hi> when with our <hi>eyes</hi> we ſee and read the contrary in the Commandement.</p>
                  <p>Further I anſwer, whereas he thinkes there is no <hi>third</hi> thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Morall and Ceremoniall, I give him this for a third thing, a <hi>perpetuall poſitive;</hi> and then though the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day was not commanded as Morall or Ceremoniall, yet it might be commanded as a perpetuall poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Ordinance.</p>
                  <p>Here againe Sir give me leave to retort your Argument upon your ſelfe on this manner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If one day of ſeven indefinitely was directly commanded as the ſubject or ſubſtance of the fourth Commandement, then it was commanded as Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or as Morall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But one day of ſeven indefinitely
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152852:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> was neither commanded as Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, nor as Morall;</hi> for there are no ſuch words in the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement as <hi>one day in ſeven;</hi> neither can they be gathered by conſequence from it: and to ſuppoſe it is but to beg the queſtion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore one day of ſeven was not commanded at all in the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the ſeventh day, which <hi>is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt</hi> in the fourth Commandement, be not commanded as the ſubject of the fourth Commandement, how ſhould one day of ſeven, which <hi>is not expreſt</hi> be the ſubject of it? And if there be no ſuch thing in the fourth Commandement as <hi>one day of ſeven indefinitely,</hi> then it is neither Moral, nor Ceremoniall, but a <hi>fantaſie</hi> of mans braine.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His third Argument.</head>
               <p>If the principall reaſons in the fourth Commandement be directly for one day in ſeven, and indirectly for that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth and laſt day of the we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke; then the fourth Commandement muſt rather be underſtood of the number, for one day
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152852:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> in ſeven, then for the order, the laſt day of ſeven.</p>
               <p>But the reaſons are directly for one day in ſeven, and indirectly for that ſeventh and laſt day of ſeven, as being the day then appointed, <hi>Ergo</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>I ſee all along hitherto that Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> ſticks much at this <hi>ordinall</hi> number ſeventh in the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and will nor endure this word <hi>order;</hi> it ſeemes to me he had rather be out of order than in order, fearing that Gods order may make him turne <hi>Jew</hi> and keep the Saturday-Sabbath: for rather than he will admit of Gods order, the ordinall ſeventh, which implies the daies put into order, he will invent an Expoſition of his own, which is without order, as one day of ſeven.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, I have this one thing againſt his Argument, that he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes <hi>comparatively,</hi> noted by the word <hi>rather,</hi> when he ſhould diſpute <hi>abſolutely,</hi> and <hi>poſitively;</hi> for our queſtion is not whether the fourth Commandement muſt <hi>rather</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152852:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> of one day in ſeven than of the ſeventh day; but abſolutely and poſitively whether it <hi>ought</hi> to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of the ſeventh day, or not of the ſeventh day; or whether it ought to be expounded of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, or of one day in ſeven, uncertainely which day; wherefore Sir, I deſire you to take home this Argument againe, and frame it anew, and ſee then if you can make any thing or nothing of it.</p>
                  <p>I have yet another thing againſt this Argument; whereas you do <hi>compare</hi> theſe two together, one day of ſeven and the ſeventh day, ſaying, the one muſt <hi>rather</hi> be taken than the other; here you compare <hi>ens</hi> with <hi>non ens;</hi> a thing which hath a <hi>being</hi> in the fourth Commandement, as the ſeventh day expreſſed, with that which hath <hi>no being</hi> in the fourth Commandement, as one day of ſeven indefinitely, which is neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed nor implied, but is a meere fiction of your own; remember Sir, that this is the place where you are to prove, if you can, that one day of ſeven indefinitly, that is, any one day of the ſeven is the ſenſe and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152852:32"/> of the fourth Commandement; but inſtead of proving it, you ſleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take it for granted you in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon <hi>rather,</hi> &amp;c. and is not this <hi>petere principium,</hi> plainly to <hi>beg the queſtion?</hi> for the comparative degree doth ſuppoſe the <hi>poſitive</hi> as granted; As for the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſhop,</hi> Dr <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ylin,</hi> and Mr <hi>Primroſe,</hi> you often <hi>taxe</hi> ſome of them for begging the queſtion, and are you, Sir, ſo frequent in the uſe of this peece of <hi>Sophiſtry?</hi> This is not the firſt time I have taken you guilty, nor will it be the laſt time.</p>
                  <p>Againe, whereas you ſay, the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> in the fourth Commandement are <hi>directly</hi> for one day in ſeven, and but <hi>indirectly</hi> for the ſeventh day.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Is it not ſtrange that what is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed ſhould be indirectly in the Commandement, and what is not expreſſed ſhould be directly in it?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As for the two reaſons menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by him, the <hi>farmer</hi> is the <hi>ſixe daies labour,</hi> whereby God perſwades us to give him the ſeventh day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath allowed us ſixe daies for our ſelves; now foraſmuch as our ſixe daies labour muſt go <hi>toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> in labour, therefore this reaſon
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152852:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> muſt be for the ſeventh and laſt day, not for one day of ſeven, or any one day of ſeven: for the ſixe labouring daies going together, theſe are the <hi>reaſons;</hi> now a reaſon cannot prove it ſelfe but another thing.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>latter</hi> reaſon, mentioned by him in page 268. and page 42. is <hi>Gods example</hi> in reſting the ſeventh day, which example leades us to the ſeventh day alſo, not unto one day of the ſeven indefinitely: for <hi>exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> lead us to follow them as <hi>neare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> as <hi>cloſely,</hi> and as <hi>exactly</hi> as we can, as <hi>Copies</hi> ſet to Schollars, and <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plers</hi> for Girles to ſew by; and ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> was to make the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> after the <hi>paterne</hi> which God ſhewed him in the Mount, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.40. now we then imitate God, and follow his example wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n we keep the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke, for it is as neere to God as poſſibly we can come; ſo you ſee the reaſons of the Commandement are plainly for the ſeventh day only.</p>
                  <p>But Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> would have one day, or any one day of the ſeven for his Sabbath, and is this to <hi>imitate</hi> God? Or rather to <hi>croſſe</hi> God? For
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152852:33"/> when God reſted on the ſeventh and <hi>laſt</hi> day of the weeke we will reſt on the firſt day, at the <hi>beginning</hi> of the weeke, and yet not <hi>aſhamed</hi> to ſay we <hi>imitate</hi> God, and follow his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; yet, but ſaith Mr <hi>Cawdry,</hi> God reſt d one day of ſeven, and if we do ſo we imitate God. I Sir, but do you imitate God as <hi>neerely,</hi> as <hi>cloſely,</hi> and as <hi>exactly</hi> as you can, or as is poſſible? And as S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>holars do, or ought their Cop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es? And as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did about th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bernacle? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is no impoſſible thing for us to keep the Saturday for our Sabbath; but as Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> loves not Gods <hi>ordinall</hi> number, the ſeventh, leſt he ſhould fall into Gods <hi>order,</hi> and ſo turne <hi>Jew:</hi> ſo he loves not to <hi>imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi> God, leſt he ſhould turne <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batarian;</hi> if he ſhould follow Gods example ſo exactly and cloſely as he may or can do, then he ſhould be too too <hi>like</hi> God, and <hi>reſemble</hi> God too much.</p>
                  <p>For concluſion, here againe, Sir, give me leave to retort this your Argument on this manner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If the principall reaſons in the fourth Commandement be directly for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152852:33"/> day, and indirectly for one day in ſeven, then the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt rather be underſtood of the ſeventh day than of one day in ſeven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the reaſons are directly for the ſeventh day, and indirectly for one day in ſeven,</hi> as you have ſeen it proved before, <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His fourth Argument.</head>
               <p>If God intended the Jews ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſanctifie the ſeventh part of their time than the ſeventh day, then the fourth Commandement doth more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly command one day in ſeven than that ſeventh day.</p>
               <p>But God intended that the Jews ſhould rather ſanctifie the ſeventh part of their time than the ſeventh day, <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>I pray Sir, what difference make you of theſe two, the ſeventh part of the Jews time and their ſeventh day? Will you compare a thing with it ſelfe? And make a ſhew of two things where there is but one
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152852:34"/> in divers words? Did not <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and others of the Jews give God both the ſeventh part of their time, and alſo the ſeventh day? And doth not Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> give Chriſt both the firſt part of his time, and alſo the firſt day? For ever ſince he was borne, or made conſcience of the Lords day, which is the <hi>firſt day</hi> of the weeke, hath he not given Chriſt both his firſt part of time, and alſo his firſt day? a worthy compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon!</p>
                  <p>Againe, you diſpute <hi>comparative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> whereas you ſhould diſpute <hi>poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively</hi> and abſolutely, as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and here againe you have Mr <hi>Cawdry's petitio principii,</hi> begging his queſtion where he ſhould have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it, if he could; is this the way to prove that <hi>one day in ſeven</hi> is the true expoſition of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement? If it be, <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> is the way; now for theſe two faults men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned I reject your Argument, and deſire you to take it home againe, and amend them, and then ſend it abroad againe, to try if it may find any better ſucceſſe.</p>
                  <p>As for your reaſon of the <hi>ſequell,</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:152852:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> you ſay, it is becauſe <hi>ſo it may extend to us Gentiles alſo.</hi> I pray Sir, why may not the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke extend to us <hi>Gentiles</hi> as well as any one day of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</p>
                  <p>But you thinke, Sir, that it was both <hi>uncertaine</hi> whether the Jews did <hi>preciſely</hi> keep the ſeventh day or not, and that in ſome caſe it was <hi>impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> to be kept. I anſwer, 1. It mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not whether it be certaine or not that the Jews kept the ſeventh day: for we diſpute not <hi>de facto,</hi> but <hi>de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> of what they did do, but of what they ought to do. 2. Why may it not be as certaine that the Jews kept the ſeventh day, as that they kept your <hi>one day of ſeven?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for the <hi>impoſſibility</hi> of their keeping it, becauſe once the <hi>Sun ſtood ſtill</hi> in <hi>Joſhuah's</hi> time; To this I ſay, this ſtanding ſtill of the Sun m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de that day a <hi>longer</hi> day than any other day of that weeke, but not <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> day: as if it ſtood ſtill on Friday the ſixth day of the weeke, yet Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday next was the ſeventh day, and ſo might poſſibly be kept.</p>
                  <p>I but, in regard of the Jews <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſions,</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:152852:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> as when they were carried into <hi>captivity</hi> in remote Countries, they could not <hi>poſſibly</hi> keep one and the ſame day for the Sabbath: for the daies in places of a different Longitude begin at different times, and as ſome ſay, the beginning of the daies differ ſo much as the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> loſt a day in ſurrounding the World.</p>
                  <p>To theſe I anſwer; 1. If theſe things be ſo, how do the Jews keep the Sabbath day now at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and in other places of the world where they live? and how do we in <hi>England</hi> keep the <hi>Lords day?</hi> For our <hi>daies</hi> differ in their beginning from the daies at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> where Chriſt roſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The ground of this errour lies in this, that they thinke when God commanded the Sabbath day at Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> he intended that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therſoever his people travelled their Sabbath muſt begin at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame point of time that it began at mount <hi>Sinai;</hi> the which is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and ſo God ſhould command his people an <hi>impoſſible</hi> thing; for when they travelled from <hi>Sinai</hi> to the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152852:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> remoteſt parts in <hi>Canaan</hi> the daies had ſome difference in beginning.</p>
                  <p>Againe, the word <hi>day</hi> ſignifies the time of <hi>light, Gen.</hi> 1.5, <hi>God called the light day,</hi> and ſo the ſeventh day is the ſeventh light; now when the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth light began in every horizon, then the ſeventh day began, be it ſooner or latter; and this is all that God intended in his fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, give me leave, Sir, to retort this your Argument alſo, in this manner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If God intended the Jews ſhould rather ſanctifie the ſeventh day than the ſeventh part of their time; then the fourth Commandement doth more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly command the ſeventh day than one day in ſeven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But God intended that the Jews ſhould rather ſanctifie the ſeventh day than the ſeventh part of their time, Ergo, &amp;c.</hi> I ſhall as ſoone make this Argument good, as you ſhall make yours good, as appeares by my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to your Argument.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>His fifth Argument.</head>
               <p>If the fourth Commandement did directly, or as the ſubſtance of it, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152852:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſeventh-day-Sabbath, then either we Chriſtians muſt keep the ſame day ſtill, or elſe the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is utterly void and aboliſhed.</p>
               <p>But we muſt neither keepe that day ſtill, nor is the fourth Commandement, void and aboliſhed. E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>go.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>As for his major I grant it; and himſelfe <hi>confirmes</hi> it, ſaying, the Commandement is <hi>morall</hi> as well as the other Laws in the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> for our <hi>Saviour</hi> confirmes it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18. ſaying, not one <hi>jot</hi> or <hi>tittle</hi> of the <hi>Law</hi> ſhall paſſe away, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now the the ſeventh-day-Sabbath is more than a <hi>jot</hi> or <hi>tittle</hi> of the fourth Commandement wherefore we muſt turne <hi>Sabbatarians,</hi> or elſe the fourth Commandement is void and aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; thus ſaith Mr <hi>Cawdry.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for his minor, I utterly deny the former part of it, ſaying <hi>we muſt not keepe that day ſtill;</hi> meaning it of the ſeventh day. But why ſo? I pray Sir, what hinders but that we may keepe the old Sabbath day ſtill? If it <hi>pleaſed you</hi> to keep it as it <hi>pleaſed
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152852:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> God</hi> to command it, <hi>Exo.</hi> 20.8. and as it <hi>pleaſed Chriſt</hi> to ratifie it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18. I know nothing againſt our keeping it but your, and other mens <hi>ſlanderous</hi> words of it, as that it is <hi>Judaiſme,</hi> and we muſt turne Jews to loath Gods people of his Sabbath. But do you thinke God commanded any thing in his ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the doing whereof, would make <hi>Chriſtians</hi> turne <hi>Jews?</hi> is any thing in the fourth Commandement <hi>Ceremoniall,</hi> ſhadowing out Chriſt as yet to come in the fleſh? If in this ſenſe we ſhould keep the Sabbath, it were properly called Judaiſme: but where is the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> that keeps it in this ſenſe, or deſires to keepe it in this ſenſe?</p>
                  <p>But ſince he hath not <hi>proved</hi> this former part of his Aſſumption, I may ſafely <hi>deny</hi> it: and ſo this his fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument ſtands for a <hi>Cypher;</hi> ſo ſtil you ſee how far Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> falls ſhort of proving by theſe Arguments that the ſeventh day is not commanded as the ſubſtance of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and that <hi>one day of ſeven</hi> is the ſubſtance of it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:152852:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>His ſixth and laſt Argument.</head>
               <p>If the ſeventh-day-Sabbath was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly commanded in the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, then there can no ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient reaſon be given why the fourth Commandement ſhould be put into the Decalogue, and not amongſt other Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall Commandements peculiar to the Jews.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Anſwer.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. I anſwer to his propoſition thus: why may there not be as good reaſon given, and as ſufficient, for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth-day-Sabbath to be put into the Decalogue, as for <hi>one day in ſeven in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitely,</hi> which never was in the fourth Commandement, or in the Decalogue, neither expreſſely, nor by conſequence.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whereas you ſay, the fourth Commandement muſt not be put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Decalogue among the Morals, but amongſt the <hi>Ceremonials;</hi> it muſt be ſo, becauſe you take it for gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the ſeventh-day-Sabbath was a <hi>Ceremony;</hi> and is not this to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152852:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>beg</hi> a <hi>queſtion?</hi> For you do not ſo much as attempt to prove it a Ceremony; and I beleeve all the skill you have cannot prove it a Ceremony; ſo by this A gument you do but beg a queſtion, which you ſhould have proved, but have not, nor can prove it; but <hi>begging the queſtion</hi> when, and where you ſhould prove it, is no rare thing with you: this is your <hi>Logick,</hi> whereby you would prove that the fourth Commandement is to be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded</hi> for <hi>one day of ſeven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I have now made punctuall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers unto all Mr <hi>Cawdry's</hi> ſixe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, whereby he hath endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, but all in vaine, to prove that the ſeventh-day Sabbath is not <hi>directly</hi> and <hi>expreſſely</hi> commanded in the fourth Commandement, a thing ſo ſtrangely <hi>abſurd,</hi> that I never read any <hi>Author</hi> beſides himſelfe to deny it; and beſides, he hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured, though alſo in vaine, to prove, that <hi>one day in ſeven</hi> indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely, that is, any one day of the ſeven is directly commanded in the fourth Commandement; and that this is the true expoſition, ſenſe, and meaning of the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152852:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> but never did <hi>Jeſuite</hi> more ſhamefully corrupt the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement about <hi>Images,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scripture, than Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> hath corrupted Gods fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as appeares by my ſeverall anſwers to his ſixe Arguments; He hath done good ſervice to Almighty God to uſe his <hi>wits</hi> to overthrow his <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> and corrupt one of his <hi>Ten</hi> Commandements: wherefore he may expect his <hi>reward</hi> when God ſhall come to give every one accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as his own <hi>works</hi> have beene.</p>
                  <p>Having <hi>vindicated</hi> the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement from Mr <hi>Cawdry's</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt gloſſes, and falſe Expoſition of it: now in the laſt place I ſhall <hi>prove</hi> againſt Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> that one day of ſeven is not the ſenſe and meaning of the fourth Commandement, but the ſeventh and laſt day of the week, which fals upon our Saturday; in my proofe whereof Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> ſhall ſee that we have many more Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments out of the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove this point than the <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall</hi> number <hi>ſeventh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the great paines Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> hath taken to draw the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152852:38"/> to the expoſition of <hi>one day in ſeven;</hi> and alſo, for that by this <hi>Expoſition</hi> he hath made <hi>anſwer</hi> to many of my twenty foure Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; hereby you may perceive that the maine and chiefe controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie about the <hi>Sabbath</hi> will be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by <hi>his</hi> or <hi>n y</hi> Expoſition of the fourth Commandement; wherefore I ſhall be the larger in proving my <hi>Expoſition</hi> for the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke: and ſo I come to prove this point;</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>That the fourth Commandement ought not to be expounded for one day of ſeven, but of the ſeventh and laſt day of ſeven definitely.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Argument the firſt.</head>
                  <p>My firſt Argument ſhall be taken out of the <hi>firſt</hi> words of the fourth Commandement, <hi>Remember the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day.</hi> This word <hi>Sabbath,</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, ſignifies <hi>Reſt;</hi> but there is more in it than ſo: for it is alſo a <hi>proper name</hi> for one of the daies of the weeke, as for the ſeventh and laſt day, which is our Saturday, like
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152852:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> as <hi>Lords day</hi> is a proper name for the firſt day of the weeke, which is our Sunday; and thus I prove it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Whereſoever in the Old or New Teſtaments you read the word <hi>Sabbath,</hi> it being ſpoken of a <hi>week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly day,</hi> it is never uſed but for a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per name for one of the weeke daies, as for Saturday the Seventh and laſt day of the weeke; no inſtance can be given to the contrary. 2. The <hi>Jews</hi> did antiently reckon their daies of the weeke thus, Satu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>day they called <hi>Sabbathum,</hi> Sabbath day; Sunday they called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.1. the firſt day of the Sabbath; Munday the ſecond of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bbath <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yea, the Jews now at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> call Saturday the Sabbath day; ſo ſtill it is uſed for a proper name for our Saturday. 3. The <hi>Latines</hi> call our Saturday <hi>Sabbatum</hi> the Sabbath day, as is to be ſeene in all Latine <hi>Dictionaries;</hi> yea, it is ſo in <hi>England;</hi> for when a <hi>Writ</hi> comes downe from the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Courts for a mans appearance, if it be for his appearance on Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, it is written <hi>Sabbatum,</hi> and <hi>die Sabbati.</hi> 4. I appeale to all Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152852:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> if the word <hi>Sabbatum</hi> be not uſed in the antient <hi>Hiſtories</hi> of the Church for Saturday the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke. Thus you ſee that <hi>Sabbath day</hi> is a proper name for our Saturday the ſeventh day; now proper names of things are <hi>definite,</hi> not <hi>indefinite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> they do limit the thing named to one cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine individuall thing, and leave it not at <hi>rovers</hi> and uncertainties, as unto any one thing, or as unto <hi>any one day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f the ſeven,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Cawdry</hi>'s idle fancy is. I cannot ſpare a man ſo groſſely abſurd in expounding Gods fourth Commandement.</p>
                  <p>But againſt this it is objected, that Sabbath day is no proper name, but a <hi>common</hi> name; for the <hi>yearely</hi> feſtivals were alſo called <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, Levit.</hi> 23.24. To this I anſwer, 1. We ſpeake of <hi>weekely</hi> dayes, and in relation to the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not of yearely daies, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to ceremoniall Laws. 2. It will no more hinder the Sabbath day to be a proper name for one of the week daies, than it will hinder the names of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> for proper names of two Apoſtles, becauſe other men
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:152852:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> then living, and no Apoſtles, have the ſame names; ſo far of my firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Argument the ſecond.</head>
                  <p>My ſecond Argument ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the <hi>middle</hi> part of the fourth Commandement, ſaying, <hi>But the ſeventh day is the Sabbath,</hi> &amp;c. for the right underſtanding and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of this word <hi>ſeventh,</hi> we muſt know there are two ſorts of numbers, a <hi>Cardinall,</hi> and an <hi>O dinal;</hi> the Cardinall numbers are theſe, one, two, three, foure, five, ſixe, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now theſe comprize <hi>all</hi> the the things numbred without diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; the <hi>Ordinall</hi> numbers are theſe, firſt, ſecond, third, fourth, fifth, ſixth, ſeventh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> now theſe notifie not <hi>all,</hi> but <hi>one</hi> of the things num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and conſiders that one in a due <hi>order</hi> for the laſt of the things num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred as for the ſeventh which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the ſixth going in order before it, not any one of them without difference<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as when we ſay, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day of the <hi>month,</hi> we meane not as Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> would, any one of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152852:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſeven daies, but the laſt of the ſeven daies which follow the ſixe daies in order before it. And by the ſeventh yeare of the <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ngs Reigne</hi> is not underſtood one of the ſeven yeares indefinitely, but the laſt yeare of the ſeven definitely and preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. So this word <hi>ſeventh</hi> in the fourth Commandement is not a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall, but an ordinall number, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying not any one of the ſeven daies, but the ſeventh and laſt day of the ſeven, which is our Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</p>
                  <p>Our <hi>Sunday</hi> or <hi>Lords day</hi> is often in Scripture called the <hi>firſt day of the weeke, Mat.</hi> 28.1. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.2, 9. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.1, 19. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2. now then reckon onwards, and <hi>Saturday</hi> will be the ſeventh and <hi>laſt</hi> day of the weeke; As there is but one Lords day, or one <hi>firſt</hi> day of the weeke, ſo reckoning onward there can be but one Saturday, or one <hi>ſeventh</hi> day of the weeke, which muſt needs be a definite and certain day; now Saturday is no uncertaine day at <hi>rovers,</hi> or any one of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven daies, uncertaine which day it is: ſo the fourth Commandement is
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152852:41"/> to be expounded of Saturday, and the ſeventh day, or laſt day of the ſeven definitely, not of any day of the ſeven.</p>
                  <p>I know they uſe to object a tenth deale of flower, and a fourth part of an hin of oyle, but this will not make the ſeventh yeare of the <hi>Kings Reigne</hi> to be any one of the ſeven yeares: nor will it make the <hi>Lords day,</hi> which is the <hi>firſt day</hi> of the weeke, to be any one day of the weeke, uncertaine which day it is; but to this I have anſwered fully be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in my anſwer to his third in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and ſhall not here repeat it; ſo far of my ſecond Argument, wherein the point is proved both by the ordinall ſeventh in the fourth Commandement, and alſo by the ordinall <hi>firſt</hi> aſcribed to the <hi>Lords day.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Argument the third.</head>
                  <p>My third Argument ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the <hi>laſt</hi> part of the fourth Commandement, ſaying, <hi>For God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the ſeventh day, and ſanctified the Sabbath day:</hi> ſo here we have the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:152852:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſeventh day men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ioned <hi>before</hi> in the Commandement, <hi>Exod</hi> 20.10. repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Sabbath day, mentioned <hi>before</hi> in the Commandement, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.8. repeated alſo; whence I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the words <hi>Sabbath day</hi> at the <hi>beginning</hi> of the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the ſame words at the <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> of the Commandement ſpeake both of one and the ſame revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of time and day; and the words <hi>ſeventh day</hi> in the former part of the Commandement, and the ſame words repeated in the latter part of the Commandement are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the ſame time and day.</p>
                  <p>For 1. In a <hi>continued</hi> ſpeech, <hi>one</hi> word or phraſe often repeated is to be underſtood in <hi>one</hi> and the ſame ſenſe, ſo as if in the latter part of the ſpeech the words be <hi>definite,</hi> then ſo they muſt be in the former part al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. 2. Gods <hi>reſt</hi> on the ſeventh day, and <hi>ſanctifying</hi> the Sabbath day, are brought as an Argument, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or motive to perſwade men to keepe this ſeventh-day Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath; now the ſame words in the <hi>queſtion</hi> or concluſion, repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the <hi>Argument</hi> or motive, muſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152852:42"/> have one and the ſame ſenſe if there be faire dealing: ſo as if the one be to be underſtood <hi>definitely,</hi> and of a time certaine, then ſo muſt the other be underſtood alſo. 3. Theſe words, the ſeventh daies reſt of God, and Gods ſanctifying the Sabbath day, are propounded as Gods <hi>example</hi> for us to <hi>imitate</hi> and follow; now the <hi>Scholar</hi> muſt follow his Copy as neare as poſſibly he can; <hi>Moſes</hi> was to follow Gods <hi>paterne</hi> of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, even to an haires breadth if poſſible: ſo are we to imitate Gods example by keeping the <hi>ſame</hi> ſeventh-day-Sabbath weekly which God kept at the Creation.</p>
                  <p>By theſe three reaſons it appeares, that being the ſame words muſt have the ſame ſenſe in all the fourth Commandement, and that the day wherein God reſted at the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and which then he ſanctified, being it was the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke, folloWing his ſixe daies creating, it was not any <hi>one day of the ſeven,</hi> but the laſt day of the ſeven definitely; therefore the fourth Commandement is to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded throughout, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152852:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> to the ending of it; for the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke, which is a fixed, limited, and defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite day, not a day at randome, ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and uncertaine, as any <hi>one day of the ſeven.</hi> The day, I ſay, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God reſted at the Creation, being ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tainly the ſeventh, and laſt day of the ſeven, or weeke; the whole fourth Commandement muſt be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the ſame ſeventh, and laſt day of the ſeven, or weeke certainly, not at rovers, as appeares by my three reaſons given; ſo far of my third Argument.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Argument the fourth.</head>
                  <p>My fourth Argument ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the <hi>body</hi> of the fourth Commandement, ſaying, <hi>Sixe daies ſhalt thou labour, but the ſeventh day thou ſhalt reſt,</hi> Exod. 20.9, 10. <hi>For in ſixe daies the Lord made the heaven and the earth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and he reſted the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day,</hi> Exod. 20.11. whence I note, that the ſixe daies, wherein God created the world, were his working daies, and they all went <hi>together,</hi> no reſting or Sabbath day comming be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152852:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> them: and the ſixe working daies of man went alſo <hi>all together,</hi> no reſting or Sabbath day comming betweene them; whence it follows, that of neceſſity the Sabbath day, in the fourth Commandement, could not poſſibly be <hi>appointed</hi> for <hi>one day of ſeven indefinitely,</hi> that is, for any one day of the ſeven indifferently; for the ſixe daies labour ought to go together for working daies; and therefore the Sabbath day could not come in betweene any of the ſixe working daies, or be any one of them; wherefore of neceſſity the Sabbath day muſt fall after the ſixe working daies, upon the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke, and not upon any <hi>one of the ſeven daies;</hi> ſo far of my fourth Argument.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Argument the fifth.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If there never was from the giving of the Law upon Mount</hi> Sinai <hi>downe to our times any day known in the Churches, but one weekly day for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day; nor any day known for the Sabbath day weekly but one, namely,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152852:43"/> Saturday the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke; then the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement ought to be expounded of that one ſeventh day definitely, and of that one Sabbath day, namely, Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day the ſeventh and laſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y of the weeke: and not for any one of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven daies, or for a Sabbath day at rovers and uncertainly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But there never was from the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Law upon Mount</hi> Sinai <hi>down to our times any day known in the Churches, but one weekely day for the ſeventh day; nor any day known for the Sabbath day weekly but one, namely, Saturday the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore the fourth Commandement ought to be expounded of that one ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day definitely, and of that one Sabbath day, namely, Saturday the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth and laſt day of the weeke: and not for any one of the ſeven daies, or for a Sabbath day at rovers and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for the firſt propoſition, it is ſo cleare as it needs no proofe; only remember this, that we ſpeake of a Sabbath <hi>weekly,</hi> not of any anniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152852:44"/> and <hi>yearely</hi> Sabbath, which belonged not to the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, but to their ſeverall and ceremoniall Commandements: but we have to do only with the fourth Commandement, and the weekely Sabbaths in relation to it. And ſo I come to prove my ſecond Propoſition in both the parts.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. At the Creation God began to number the daies of the weeke by theſe <hi>ordinall</hi> numbers, the firſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, third, fourth, fifth, ſixth, and the <hi>laſt</hi> was the ſeventh day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.5, 8, &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.2, 3. this numbring of the weeke daies continued in the Church unto the giving of the <hi>Law</hi> upon Mount <hi>Sinai, Exod.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.9, 10. from thence it continued in the Church untill <hi>Chriſts time, Mat.</hi> 28.1. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16 2, 9. and in all theſe times no day was known to be the ſeventh but one, namely, Saturday; and from Chriſts time unto <hi>ours</hi> it is ſtill ſo known: for all Divines, Antient, and Moderne, call our Sunday, or <hi>Lords day,</hi> the <hi>firſt</hi> day of the weeke, and ſo conſequently Saturday if you reckon onwards the ſeventh day; ſo
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:152852:44"/> there being no ſeventh day but one, namely Saturday, the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement muſt be expounded of Saturday the ſeventh day, and not of one day in ſeven uncertainly.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As for the name <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> it began in the Church for a weekly day before the giving of the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>w, Exod.</hi> 16.22, 23. from thence unto the giving of the Law it continued for a weekly day, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.8, 9 10. from the giving of the Law unto <hi>Chriſt</hi> it ſtill continued in the Church, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.2, 6. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13. <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h.</hi> 13.15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28 1. <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.56. with <hi>Luk.</hi> 24 1. and from Chriſt's time in hath continued unto our time; for Eccleſiaſticall <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtorians</hi> antiently uſed the name Sabbath day for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday; the <hi>Latines</hi> do ſo to this day, and in <hi>England,</hi> as in the caſe of a <hi>Writ,</hi> we do the ſame, as I have ſhew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> before; wherefore ſince there never was, nor is known in the Churches, any weekly day named <hi>Sabbath day</hi> but one, namely Saturday; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the fourth Commandement muſt be expounded of this one day Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday, the ſeventh and laſt day of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152852:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> the weeke, and not of a Sabbath day indefinitely, as uncertaine which day it is; thus you have ſeene this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument proved.</p>
                  <p>But it will be ſaid, Is not our <hi>Lords day</hi> commonly called <hi>Sabbath day</hi> in all <hi>Pulpits,</hi> and in all <hi>Books?</hi> I anſwer, yea: it is ſo called by ſuch as love to <hi>miſcall</hi> things, and to <hi>nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name</hi> daies; ſo they may call if they pleaſe every <hi>Faſt day,</hi> every <hi>Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving day,</hi> &amp; every <hi>Chriſtmas day</hi> But ſure I am, this is but a <hi>novelty</hi> of <hi>ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdaies</hi> ſtanding; and as the <hi>name</hi> is novell, ſo is the <hi>obſervation</hi> of the Lords day, as, or for a Sabbath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell alſo, as by and by you ſhall ſee: For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Lords day was never cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Sabbath day in any <hi>Scripture</hi> of the New Teſtament; let them ſhew us a Text for it if they can.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Theſe Authors before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, St <hi>Auguſtine, Peter Martyr, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, Zanchie, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus, Paraeus, Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitius, Melanchion,</hi> with many others, all theſe wrote of the <hi>Lords day;</hi> that it is but an <hi>indifferent</hi> thing, and of the ſame authority with <hi>Good Friday</hi>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:152852:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Paſſion day, <hi>Chriſtmas day,</hi> and o her <hi>holy daies</hi> of the Church; and therefore theſe men could not think in their times the Lords day was a Sabbath: or call the Lords day Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, as we do in reference to the fourth Commandement.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In the fifth yeare of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth an Act was made for the keeping of <hi>Holy daies,</hi> as <hi>Sunday,</hi> St <hi>Matthews</hi> day, St <hi>Marks</hi> day, and the other holy daies: In which <hi>Act,</hi> both the <hi>King,</hi> the Lords ſpirituall the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> the <hi>Lords</hi> Temporall, and the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> expreſſely confeſſed that they knew no <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> for <hi>Sunday,</hi> or the other <hi>Holy daies,</hi> and therefore they could not call Sunday, or St <hi>Matthews</hi> day Sabbath daies, and therefore this nicknaming of daies, as to call the Sunday and Lords day Sabbath day, and to keepe it as a Sabbath, is but a <hi>novelty,</hi> and ſprang up but ſince <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth his daies.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. I am ſixty foure yeares of Age, and ſo cannot remember much above fifty yeares, yet I do remember ſuch works commonly done on the <hi>Lords
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152852:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> day,</hi> as I am ſure are no Sabbath days works: For in the City of <hi>Norwich,</hi> about fifty yeares ago, the City <hi>Waits,</hi> or Muſitians were wont for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers weekes in the yeare to play upon the Market <hi>Croſſe</hi> on the latter pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t of the Lords day, thouſands of people there aſſembled to heare them. At the new elected <hi>Majors</hi> gate they played at <hi>Waſters</hi> or Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels on the latter part of the Lords day, with hundreds of people look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on. And the Sealing <hi>Office</hi> was open, and Weavers carrying and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrying their S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uffs to be ſealed. The Merchants bought their S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uff; on the Lords day, and packed them in great packs the ſame day: and the <hi>Carts</hi> loaded the Stuffs the ſame day at night, and went towards <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> by foure a clock the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; theſe things were done with the knowledge of all the <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> and without contradiction of the moſt godly <hi>Miniſters.</hi> I have been credibly informed, that about ten yeares before my time a <hi>religious Grocer</hi> in the City did open his ſhop ordinarily on the <hi>Lords day,</hi> and Mr
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:152852:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>Moore,</hi> the moſt religious <hi>Miniſter</hi> then in the City, hath come into the Shop, ſeeing them buying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Grocery wares, and did never rebuke them for it, or ſay, why do you ſo? And another antient and religious man a <hi>Shooemaker</hi> told me this day, that in his younger time <hi>Shooemakers</hi> ſold ſhooes on the Lords day ordinarily; wherefore the <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> of the <hi>Lords day</hi> as a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day is but a <hi>novel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y,</hi> and they that <hi>thus kept it</hi> could not <hi>thinke</hi> it was a Sabbath day, or <hi>call</hi> it a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day; ſo far of my fifth Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Argument the ſixth.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If the fourth Commandement was expounded by</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets for Saturday the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke, and not for Sunday the firſt day of the weeke, or any one day of the ſeven; then the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is now to be expounded for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday the ſeventh and laſt day of the we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ke, and not for Sunday the firſt day of the weeke, or for any one day of the ſeven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:152852:47"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the fourth Commandement was expounded by</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets for Saturday the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke, and not for Sunday <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he firſt day of the weeke; or for one da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of ſeven:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ought in our times to be expounded for Saturday the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke, not for Sunday the firſt day of the weeke, or for any one day of the ſeven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt <hi>propoſition,</hi> it ſtands firme by this reaſon; Looke what was once the true ſenſe and meaning of Gods <hi>Laws,</hi> the ſame is the ſenſe and meaning of it for ever after: for the <hi>ſenſe</hi> and meaning of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture do not vary and change with the change of time<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; as if Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had one expoſition and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to day, and another to morrow; we can find no better rule for the expounding of any Text of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the Old Teſtament, than to expound it as <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> did antiently; If therefore the fourth Commandement was antiently <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded</hi> for Saturday, it muſt be ſo
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152852:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> expounded ſtill, and in our times. Take a ceremoniall Law, as that of <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> or the <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> and if you will expound and open the ſenſe of it now, you muſt render the ſame ſenſe of it now which <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets gave of it antient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or elſe your expoſition is falſe; I do not ſay a ceremoniall Law <hi>binds</hi> now as it did antiently, but yet I ſay the <hi>expoſition</hi> of it is the ſame now which it was antiently: as if you fall upon expoſition of the <hi>time</hi> and <hi>day</hi> of Circumciſion, or the Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, you muſt expound it now of the eighth <hi>day,</hi> not of the ſeventh or ninth day: and of the foureteenth day of the <hi>month,</hi> not of the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of the <hi>yeare;</hi> and ſo you muſt deale with every of the ten mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Commandements, or elſe you deale falſely with them.</p>
                  <p>As for the ſecond <hi>Prepoſition,</hi> it is cleare that <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> did expound the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to their people the Jews for Saturday the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke, not for Sunday the firſt day of the weeke, or for any <hi>one
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:152852:48"/> day of the ſeven,</hi> becauſe the Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were taught and inſtructed by <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> kept the Saturday, and not the Sunday by the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement; yea, this Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, ſaying, <hi>The ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke was appointed to the old world.</hi> that is, to the Jews; ſo far of my ſixth Argument.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Argument the ſeventh.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If the Lords day be rightly expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the firſt day of the weeke, and not for any one day of the weeke, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine which day it is, then the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day muſt be expounded for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth and laſt day of the weeke, and not for any one day of the ſeven, uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine which day it is.</hi> The reaſon hereof is one and the ſame; for when you read of a day called the <hi>Lords day, Rev.</hi> 1.10. you underſtand it of the <hi>firſt day of the weeke,</hi> and of no other day, becauſe you read elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where that Chriſt our Lord <hi>roſe</hi> on the <hi>firſt</hi> day of the weeke, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.9. ſo when we read of the <hi>Sabbath
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152852:48"/> day, Exod.</hi> 20.8. and read againe in the ſame fourth Commandement, <hi>The ſeventh day is the Sabbath, Exod.</hi> 20.10. we muſt underſtand it of the ſeventh and <hi>laſt</hi> day of the week, and of no other day; for if the <hi>ordinall</hi> number <hi>firſt</hi> be underſtood proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the firſt day of the ſeven, and not improperly for any one of the ſeven as touching the Lords day; ſo the <hi>ordinall</hi> number <hi>ſeventh</hi> muſt be underſtood properly alſo for the laſt of ſeven, not improperly for any <hi>one of the ſeven</hi> as touching the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Sabbath day; if the one be taken properly, ſo muſt the other; and if the one be take improperly, ſo may the other; ſo far of my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Argument.</p>
                  <p>Thus I have proved by ſeven Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments that the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement muſt be expounded of <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> the ſeventh and laſt day of the weeke, and not of any <hi>one of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven daies.</hi> Now for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> further <hi>vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I ſhall ſhew how <hi>abſurd</hi> it is for Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> to deny the Saturday, the ſeventh and laſt day, to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:152852:49"/> commanded in the fourth Commandement, and to expound it of a Sabbath day indefinitely, and of one day of ſeven indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Of the abſurdneſſe to reject the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the fourth Commandement for the Sabbath day definitely, and the ſeventh and laſt day of the ſeven defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely, and to expound it of a Sabbath day indefinitely, and of a ſeventh day indefinitely, or of one day in ſeven.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The firſt abſurdity.</head>
                  <p>If by the word <hi>Sabbath</hi> in the fourth Commandement we may underſtand a Sabbath day uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, as a <hi>reſt</hi> upon any of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven daies; and by the word <hi>ſeventh</hi> any one of the ſeven daies; then we may keep two Sabbath daies toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without ſix daies labour going betweene them: As for example, we may keep the <hi>Saturday</hi> the laſt of the weeke, and <hi>Sunday</hi> the firſt of the next weeke; and ſo two S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bbaths go together, no working daies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152852:49"/> betweene them, and is not this abſurd? For Saturday is one day of the ſeven in the former weeke, and Sunday after is one day of the ſeven in the latter weeke.</p>
                  <p>Againe, If the former pleaſe nor, then take this; <hi>Chriſt</hi> did lye in his grave upon Saturday, which by the <hi>Jews</hi> was kept for the Sabbath day according to the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23 56. Now if <hi>Chriſtians</hi> kept the Sunday or Lords day, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the next day following the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, were not then two Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath daies kept together without any working daies comming between them? And is not this abſurd? Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, and if <hi>both daies</hi> were kept by the fourth Commandement, is not this much more abſurd? So far of the firſt abſurdity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſecond abſurdity.</head>
                  <p>If by <hi>Sabbath</hi> we may underſtand a <hi>reſt</hi> on any day of the weeke; and by <hi>ſeventh</hi> any one of the ſeven daies; then we may keepe by the fourth Commandement <hi>Sunday</hi> the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152852:50"/> Lords day this weeke in memory of Chriſts <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and <hi>Good Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> in the next weeke, or every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Friday in the yeare in memory of Chriſts <hi>Paſſion:</hi> for as Sunday is one day of the ſeven in this weeke, ſo Friday is one day of the ſeven in the next weeke; and is not this abſurd? And to keepe theſe two daies by the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo, is not this much more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd; ſo far of the ſecond abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity.</p>
                  <p>But perhaps you will ſay, we have <hi>Scripture</hi> for the <hi>Lords day,</hi> but you have none for <hi>Good Friday.</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, If I would abuſe Scripture for Friday, as you abuſe Scripture for the Lords day, I could alledge a Text, having as much colour in it as the beſt of your Texts; ſee for this purpoſe, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10, &amp;c. <hi>They ſhall looke upon me whom they have pierced, and mourne for him, as one mourneth for his only Son.</hi> This Text may be applyed to Good Friday, wherein Chriſt was <hi>pierced</hi> for our <hi>Sins,</hi> and wrought the worke of our eternall <hi>Redemption,</hi> and ſaid upon
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152852:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> his Croſſe, now <hi>It is finiſhed, Ioh.</hi> 19.30. So we may keep the Lords day every other weeke in memory of Chriſts Reſurrection, and every other Friday as our Chriſtian Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath in memory of Chriſts Paſſion and our Redemption.</p>
                  <p>But you will ſay, the Sabbath day is a day of <hi>rejoycing,</hi> but Good Friday is a day of <hi>mourning.</hi> To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, the Sabbath day in the fourth Commandement was kept in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <hi>Creation,</hi> and yet you can keepe the Lords day by the fourth Commandement in memory of the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> why then may we not keepe ſometimes the memory of Chriſts Paſſion and our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on <hi>Friday</hi> by the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement as well as Sunday, or the Lords day, in memory of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> by the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement? but a change in both; I know indeed that this Text, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. is liable to many <hi>juſt</hi> excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſo is the <hi>beſt Text</hi> alledged by Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> for the Lords day; but would he be pleaſed to take Good Friday into his <hi>favour</hi> as he
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152852:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> hath done the Lords day, he could with a little of his <hi>Logick,</hi> mingled with much of his <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> and ſome of his <hi>Sophiſtry,</hi> make this Text, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. as plauſible a Text be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the multitude for <hi>Good Friday,</hi> as is his beſt Text for the <hi>Lords day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> And ſo I come to the third abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The third abſurdity.</head>
                  <p>If by Sabbath we may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand any day of the weeke wherein we <hi>reſt;</hi> and by ſeventh any one day of the ſeven; then firſt, The <hi>Jews</hi> were no more bound to keepe <hi>Saturday</hi> the laſt day of ſeven than to keepe the Lords day, or <hi>Sunday</hi> the firſt day of the ſeven; for the Sunday was then ſome one day of the ſeven.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Then we <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may keep the <hi>Saturday</hi> Sabbath; for this day is one day of the ſeven; but we may not keepe the Saturday, as they ſay, becauſe it is <hi>Judaiſme,</hi> as they call it; and it is expired, and aboliſhed, as they ſay.</p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:152852:51"/>
                  <p>Now are not theſe two things two abſurdities? So far of this third ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The fourth abſurdity.</head>
                  <p>To expound the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement for <hi>one day of ſeven</hi> is abſurd, becauſe we have but one day of ſixe if they <hi>reject</hi> the ſeventh and laſt day of the <hi>weeke;</hi> take away <hi>Saturday,</hi> the ſeventh day, as an aboliſhed, or expired day, which may not be kept for feare of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſme,</hi> and then you have remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning but ſixe daies in every weeke; and therefore if you take any day of theſe ſixe daies for a Sabbath, you take but one day out of ſixe daies, not one day out of ſeven daies; for one of the ſeven daies is exempted and excepted, ſo as it may not be taken. In caſe we were wont to chooſe a <hi>Major</hi> out of ſeven Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and now the <hi>King</hi> forbids us to chooſe the laſt man of the ſeven becauſe he is ſickly, and like to dye, or dead; though antiently our choice was one out of ſeven, yet
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152852:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> now it is but one out of ſixe.</p>
                  <p>God commands to keepe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day holy, but Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> hath brought it down to <hi>one day</hi> of ſeven, and upon further ſearch it is come down to <hi>one day</hi> of ſixe; So far of this fourth Abſurdity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The fifth Abſurdity.</head>
                  <p>It is <hi>abſurd,</hi> if not alſo <hi>impious</hi> and wicked, to alter the expoſition, ſenſe, and meaning of the <hi>Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> Commandements; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt be ſo to alter the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or any of the ten <hi>morall</hi> Commandements; take theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: firſt, ſee <hi>Lev.</hi> 23.24. <hi>In the ſeventh month, and the firſt day of the month ye ſhall have a Sabbath for the remembrance of blowing the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,</hi> &amp;c. were it not an impious thing to alter the ſenſe of this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, ſaying, God intended no more by this ordinall number the ſeventh <hi>month</hi> but this, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould give him a <hi>Sabbath</hi> in any <hi>one of the ſeven months?</hi> Secondly,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152852:52"/> ſee <hi>Lev.</hi> 25.4. <hi>Sixe yeares thou ſhalt ſow thy field, but the ſeventh yeare ſhall be a Sabbath,</hi> &amp;c. Had Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> wrote in <hi>Moſes</hi> daies he could have taught the people that they might give God but ſome <hi>one</hi> or <hi>other</hi> of the ſeven <hi>yeares</hi> for a Sabbath. Thirdly, the <hi>Paſſeover</hi> was to be kept on the fourteenth day of the <hi>month;</hi> I, could Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> ſay, that is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome <hi>one</hi> or <hi>other</hi> of the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene daies. Fourthly, the eighth day was appointed for <hi>Circumciſion;</hi> yet, can Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> ſay, by this <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall</hi> number the eighth may be meant <hi>one of the eight daies,</hi> as the firſt, or third, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Fifthly, <hi>Chriſt</hi> roſe the <hi>third</hi> day, but it may be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome <hi>one</hi> of the three daies, as on the firſt day or ſecond. God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Circumciſion on the eighth day; may not Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> ſay, hence Chriſtians be bound to <hi>baptize</hi> Children on the ninth day, the day after, or on the firſt day? For he ſaith, we are to keep our <hi>Sabbath</hi> on the eighth or firſt day. Is not this to make the Scriptures a <hi>Noſe</hi> of <hi>Waxe?</hi> If it be abſurd, yea, and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152852:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> wickedly done to alter the ſenſe of of the Ceremoniall Laws, is it not ſo too to alter the ſenſe of a morall Law?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſixth Abſurdity.</head>
                  <p>Suppoſing, but not granting, that Mr <hi>Brabourne</hi> were bound in a <hi>bond</hi> to pay to Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> twenty pounds upon <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> day the twenty fifth day of <hi>December,</hi> when Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> can make him beleeve that this twenty pounds is due to him upon the <hi>firſt</hi> day of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> or upon any <hi>one</hi> of the twenty five daies of <hi>December; then</hi> ſhall he make him beleeve alſo, that <hi>when</hi> God binds men in the bond of the fourth Commandement to ſanctifie the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, the ſeventh day of the weeke, <hi>then</hi> he binds men by his bond of the fourth Commandement to ſanctifie the <hi>firſt</hi> day of the week the <hi>Lords day,</hi> or any one of the ſeven daies. Our common <hi>Lawyers</hi> in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a <hi>Bond</hi> before a Judge, would be aſhamed of ſuch <hi>Law;</hi> but our eminent <hi>Divines</hi> in preaching to the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:152852:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> people of the <hi>bond</hi> of the fourth Commandement are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot aſhamed of ſuch <hi>Divinity.</hi> Againe, <hi>when</hi> Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> will be willing to take for his <hi>tenth,</hi> or tithe <hi>Lambe</hi> any one of the ten, be it a rotten, lame, leane, or blind Lambe, <hi>then</hi> it may be he ſhall p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rſwade me, that by Gods ſeventh day we may underſtand ſome <hi>one day</hi> of the ſixe <hi>working daies.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The ſeventh Abſurdity.</head>
                  <p>All <hi>Divines</hi> that I have read, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that the ſeventh day, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday-Sabbath, was commanded to the <hi>Jews</hi> in the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement; and the <hi>Jews</hi> now living whereſoever, do keepe the Saturday by the fourth Commandement; yea, and Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> ſaith often in his Books of the Sabbath, that the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth and laſt day was appointed to the old world, that is, to the Jews; but if now, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ince <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Saturday and ſev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nth-day-Sabbath be not comamnded in the fourth Commandement, but ſome other
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152852:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>one day of ſeven,</hi> as the <hi>Lords day,</hi> the firſt day of the weeke, then the <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>meaning</hi> of the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement is <hi>altered</hi> and <hi>changed</hi> from what it was <hi>antiently,</hi> and a <hi>new</hi> ſenſe and meaning is given of it; if this be not an abſurdity, or rather a <hi>madneſſe,</hi> I know not what is.</p>
                  <p>Shall the <hi>words</hi> in the Scripture be thought to change their ſenſe with the times? Shall they have one ſenſe to day, and another to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row? Is not this the ſin of him that thought he might <hi>change times and Laws, Dan.</hi> 7.25.</p>
                  <p>That <hi>one</hi> word in <hi>divers</hi> Texts may ſignifie divers things is nothing ſtrange; but that one and the ſame word in one and the ſame Text, the fourth Commandement, ſhould ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie antiently one thing, and in our daies another thing, this is an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity matchleſſe.</p>
                  <p>That by Sabbath, and ſeventh day the fourth Commandement ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>joyne the <hi>Saturday</hi> to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the <hi>Sunday</hi> to the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> the Saturday for thouſands of years unto Chriſt, and the Sunday for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:152852:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> ever after Chriſt; this may well be called the <hi>Queene</hi> of abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
                  <p>Hath the approach of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell</hi> changed the meaning of the words in the <hi>Law?</hi> If words in the <hi>Decalogue</hi> ſhall have one ſenſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt came, and another ſenſe after Chriſts comming, there will be no certaine ſenſe of any of the ten Commandements.</p>
                  <p>Were a <hi>Schoolemaſter</hi> to conſtrue <hi>Terence,</hi> or other profane Author to his Scholars, he would be aſhamed to give any ſenſe divers from an <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient</hi> known ſenſe; but we have <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> not aſhamed to abuſe their <hi>Auditors</hi> worſe than a Schoolemaſter would abuſe his Schollers: wherefore Schoolemaſters ſhall riſe up in judgement to condemne ſuch Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; God never beſtowed wit and learning on ſuch Miniſters, and I may ſay <hi>honeſty</hi> too, to corrupt his Scriptures, and to abuſe their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors; Is this to take charge of the <hi>Soules</hi> of the people?</p>
                  <p>For my part, laying aſide the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects I beare to <hi>God,</hi> and to the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152852:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>Scriptures,</hi> I care not whether you keepe Saturday-Sabbath, Sunday-Sabbath, or Monday Sabbath; and if we kept none at all it were beſt of all: but if we have reſpect to God or to his Scriptures, let us give him the day of his own <hi>choice,</hi> not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; let us not ſo ſhamefully and abominably corrupt his Scriptures by notorious falſe expoſitions; it were far better for the Church and State to have no <hi>Scriptures,</hi> than to have Scriptures falſely expounded to the people.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The eighth Abſurdity</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Suppoſe</hi> we that <hi>Chriſt</hi> had left a Commandement in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the <hi>Lords day,</hi> as <hi>certainly God</hi> left a Commandement for <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday</hi> the ſeventh day in the Old Teſtament; and ſuppoſe that <hi>Chriſt</hi> had ſaid, <hi>Remember the Lords day to ſanctifie it; the firſt day of the weeke is the Lords day, in it thou ſhalt do no worke; for the Lord Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ed, or roſe from the dead on the firſt day of the weeke, and therefore the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152852:55"/> Lord Chriſt bleſſed the Lords day, and ſanctified it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If now Mr <hi>Brabourne</hi> ſhould <hi>preach</hi> on this Commandement, or <hi>write</hi> a <hi>book</hi> for the true Expoſition of it, and inſtruct the people of the Land, ſaying,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By the <hi>Lords day,</hi> you are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>a</hi> Lords day, but not <hi>the</hi> Lords day, for every day of the weeke is the Lord Chriſts day in ſome ſenſe. 2. By the <hi>firſt day of the weeke</hi> you may underſtand ſome <hi>one day of the weeke</hi> or other. 3. We may <hi>imitate</hi> Chriſts <hi>reſting</hi> or riſing from death, on the firſt day of the weeke, if we Chriſtians reſt upon ſome one or other day of the weeke, as on Saturday the laſt day of the weeke. 4. The Lords day was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to the <hi>Grecians</hi> in the firſt Age of the Church, but Saturday the ſeventh day to us Chriſtians. 5. The Lords day, and firſt day of the weeke are not the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of Chriſts Commandement, but Saturday the laſt of the weeke. 6 The Lords day, and firſt day of the weeke, are <hi>indirectly</hi> commanded by Chriſt,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152852:56"/> but Saturday, the ſeventh day of the weeke, are <hi>directly</hi> commanded.</p>
                  <p>Should I thus expound this Commandement of Chriſt, oh, how would the <hi>Patrons</hi> of the Lords day rage, ſtampe, and ſtorme at me? Saying, how ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully doth this <hi>Brabourne</hi> corrupt Chriſt his Law for the Lords day? How abominably doth he abuſe Gods people by his falſe Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Never did <hi>Jeſuite</hi> ſo abuſe and corrupt any Texts of Scripture as this man hath abuſed our Lord Chriſt his Commandement; the <hi>Devils</hi> themſelves did never ſo abuſe the Scriptures; it is pitty the man is ſuffered to live any longer, hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is too good for him, burne him like an Heretick, I cannot expreſſe the one halfe of their zeale in this kind; and I confeſſe all this were worthily ſpoken againſt me if I had ſo done; but now I pray <hi>compare</hi> my <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> Expoſition of Chriſts <hi>ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> Commandement with Mr <hi>Caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie's reall</hi> Expoſition of Gods reall fourth Commandement in the ſixe particulars mentioned, and behold
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152852:56"/> how <hi>paralell</hi> and <hi>alike</hi> they are one to the other point by point! now if my Expoſition be abominably ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, what then is theirs? and if <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits,</hi> yea, and the <hi>Devill</hi> never did the like, what may too many of our moſt <hi>zealous Miniſters</hi> thinke of themſelves who do the ſame d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yly, and are the moſt forward and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in this kind of expoſition? ſo far of the Abſurdities, and now I come to my Concluſion,</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>HAving vindicated God's fourth Commandement from Mr <hi>Cawdrie's</hi> falſe Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of it; now it will be expected that I ſhould proceed in <hi>anſwer</hi> to other paſſages of his <hi>Books,</hi> and in particular to confute his anſwers made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>divers</hi> of my twenty foure Arguments for the <hi>antient Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> and to anſwer or confute
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:152852:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> his Texts alleaged by him in maintenance of the <hi>Lords-day-Sabbath,</hi> as it is called now adaies; touching theſe two I ſhall give this account.</p>
            <p>Firſt, concerning the <hi>anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Sabbath;</hi> if I ſhould main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine my twenty foure Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Mr <hi>Cawdry,</hi> or ſome of his friends for him might complaine to the <hi>State,</hi> and procure my book to be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>fire</hi> as Jewiſh; for ſo was Mr <hi>Ockfords</hi> book of like kind; but I am reſolved that no provocations ſhall force me to proceed ſo far; againe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving vindicated the fourth Commandement from this falſe expoſition of <hi>one day in ſeven,</hi> I have confuted the moſt of his <hi>Anſwers</hi> given by him to many of my 24 Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſo as it is needleſſe for
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152852:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> me to proceed any further.</p>
            <p>Now as touching Mr <hi>Caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie's</hi> Texts, alledged by him to prove the <hi>Lords day</hi> to be kept for a Sabbath, if I ſhould an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer them, as nothing is more facile and eaſie to be done, I might ſo alſo run the hazzard of having my books burnt with fire, but I will not offend the <hi>State</hi> ſo far; I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſatisfie my ſelfe with this, that I have many yeares ſince diſcharged my <hi>conſcience</hi> by writing of two ſeverall books, wherein I have made anſwers plentifully to every one of their Texts of Scripture, and given not one but <hi>many</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers unto <hi>every</hi> one of their Texts of Scripture, the which <hi>anſwers were never yet confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any man,</hi> and yet it is about twenty ſixe yeares ſince
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152852:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> I wrote my firſt book, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout twenty two yeares ſince I wrote my ſecond booke; nor hath Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed thoſe anſwers, albeit he hath made a great flouriſh with three great books, ſaying, he will confute all <hi>gainſayers;</hi> but it is very falſe, for he hath not confuted Mr <hi>Brabourne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I obſerve, that albeit M. <hi>Caw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry</hi> is larger upon the Sabbath than any man, yet hath he no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>new,</hi> or more for matter than others have wrote many yeares agone; <hi>new books but old matter;</hi> more <hi>words,</hi> but no more <hi>matter;</hi> the <hi>Practice of Piety</hi> in a few leaves is as large for matter as M. <hi>Cawdries</hi> three large books of twelve ſhillings price; now ſince Mr <hi>Cawdry</hi> hath brought no new <hi>Texts</hi> of Scripture to light, or
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152852:58"/> new <hi>Arguments</hi> for the Lords day; wherefore ſhould I blot paper, and ſpend inke to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that in <hi>him</hi> which I have fully anſwered long ſince to <hi>others,</hi> who have wrote the ſame things before him?</p>
            <p>Whileſt I was in writing of my firſt booke of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and in anſwering the Texts of Scripture alledged for the <hi>Lords day,</hi> me thought they were ſuch <hi>ſimple</hi> and <hi>ſilly</hi> things for that purpoſe, as my thoughts often <hi>checked</hi> me for vouchſafing an anſwer to them, fearing underſtanding Divines would ſecretly thinke that <hi>Brabourne</hi> was ſome <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noramus,</hi> or ſome vainglorious man, labouring to gaine credit by fighting with a <hi>ſhaddow,</hi> and confuting what no judicious Schollar would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aintaine. I
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:152852:59"/> remember that divers times I tooke off my Pen to pauſe whether I ſhould go on or not, and doubtleſſe I had then broke off, but that I ſaw ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our moſt <hi>zealous</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſo far from being <hi>aſhamed</hi> of it, as they with a deale of not zeale maintained it; but I may ſay of them, as once Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of thoſe ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Jews, <hi>They have the zeale of God, but not according to knowledge, Rom.</hi> 10.2. And as Chriſt ſaid to the Scribes and Phariſees, <hi>Woe be unto you blind guides,</hi> for miſleading the <hi>devout</hi> people of the Land, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. and ſo I end.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152852:59"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
